<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-05T13:56:31+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Victory Everlasting Gospel Ministry</title><subtitle>Welcome to Victory Everlasting Gospel Ministry, an independent Seventh Day Adventist ministry based in Kenya. Our mission is to share the everlasting gospel of Jesus Christ and promote biblical truths through our various ministries and outreach programs. Our website is designed to help you learn more about our ministry, our beliefs, and our services. We offer resources such as sermons, Bible studies, and devotional materials to support your spiritual growth. We also provide information about our upcoming events and outreach programs so you can get involved and make a difference in your community. At Victory Everlasting Gospel Ministry, we are committed to helping people experience the love and grace of Jesus Christ and live a life of victory through Him. Join us in this journey and discover the joy of being part of God's family.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Pergo</title><link href="/2023/05/05/Pergo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pergo" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/05/Pergo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/05/Pergo.html"><![CDATA[<p>MAN was made in the image of God. “And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness.” “So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him.” Genesis 1:26, 27. See also chap. 9:6; 1 Corinthians 11:7. Those who deny the personality of God, say that “image” here does not mean physical form, but moral image, and they make this the grand starting point to prove the immortality of all men. The argument stands thus: First, man was made in God’s moral image. Second, God is an immortal being. Third, therefore all men are immortal. But this mode of reasoning would also prove man omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent, and thus clothe mortal man with all the attributes of the deity. Let us try it: First, man was made in God’s moral image. Second, God is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. Third, therefore, man is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. That which proves too much, proves nothing to the point, therefore the position that the image of God means his moral image, cannot be sustained. As proof that God is a person, read his own words to Moses: “And the Lord said, Behold there is a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon a rock; and it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a cleft of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand while I pass by. And I will take away mine hand and thou shalt see my back parts; but my face shall not be seen.” Exodus 33:21-23. See also chap. 24:9-11. Here God tells Moses that he shall see his form. To say that God made it appear to Moses that he saw his form, when he has no form, is charging God with adding to falsehood a sort of juggling deception upon his servant Moses.</p>

<p>But the skeptic thinks he sees a contradiction between verse 11, which says that the Lord spake unto Moses face to face, and verse 20, which states that Moses could not see his face. But let Numbers 12:5-8 remove the difficulty. “And the Lord came down in the pillar of the cloud, and stood in the door of the tabernacle, and called Aaron and Miriam, and they both came forth. And he said, Hear now my words. If there be a prophet among you, I, the Lord, will make myself known unto him in a vision, and will speak unto him in a dream. My servant Moses is not so, who is faithful in all mine house. With him will I speak mouth to mouth, <em>even apparently</em>.”</p>

<p>The great and dreadful God came down, wrapped in a cloud of glory. This cloud could be seen, but not the face which possesses more dazzling brightness than a thousand suns. Under these circumstances Moses was permitted to draw near and converse with God face to face, or mouth to mouth, <em>even apparently</em>.</p>

<p>Says the prophet Daniel, “I beheld till the thrones were cast down, and the Ancient of days did sit, whose garment was white as snow, and the hairs of his head like the pure wool; his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheels as burning fire.” Chap. 7:9. “I saw in the night visions, and, behold, one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of days, and they brought him near before him, and there was given him dominion and glory and a kingdom.” Verses 13, 14.</p>

<p>Here is a sublime description of the action of two personages; viz, God the Father, and his Son Jesus Christ. Deny their personality, and there is not a distinct idea in these quotations from Daniel. In connection with this quotation read the apostle’s declaration that the Son was in the express image of his Father’s person. “God, who at sundry times, and in divers manners, spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets, hath in these last days spoken unto us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by whom also he made the worlds; who being the brightness of his glory, and the <em>express image of his person</em>.” Hebrews 1:1-3.</p>

<p>We here add the testimony of Christ. “And the Father himself which hath sent me, hath borne witness of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his <em>shape</em>.” John 5:37. See also Philippians 2:6. To say that the Father has not a personal shape, seems the most pointed contradiction of plain scripture terms. OBJECTION. — “God is a Spirit.” John 4:24.</p>

<p>ANSWER. — Angels are also spirits [Psalm 104:4], yet those that visited Abram and Lot, lay down, ate, and took hold of Lot’s hand. They were spirit beings. So is God a Spirit being.</p>

<p>OBJ. — God is everywhere. Proof. Psalm 139:1-8. He is as much in every place as in any one place.</p>

<p>ANS. — 1. God is everywhere by virtue of his omniscience, as will be seen by the very words of David referred to above. Verses 1-6. “O Lord, thou hast searched me, and known me. Thou knowest my down-sitting and mine uprising; thou understandest my thought afar off. Thou compassest my path and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways. For there is not a word in my tongue, but, lo, O Lord, thou knowest it altogether. Thou hast beset me behind and before, and laid thy hand upon me. Such knowledge is too wonderful for me. It is high; I cannot attain unto it.”</p>

<p>2. God is everywhere by virtue of his Spirit, which is his representative, and is manifested wherever he pleases, as will be seen by the very words the objector claims, referred to above. Verses 7-10. “Whither shall I go from thy Spirit? or whither shall I flee from thy presence? If I ascend up into heaven, thou art there; if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou art there. If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea, even there shall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand shall hold me.”</p>

<p>God is in heaven. This we are taught in the Lord’s prayer. “Our Father which art in heaven.” Matthew 6:9; Luke 11:2. But if God is as much in every place as he is in any one place, then heaven is also as much in every place as it is in any one place, and the idea of going to heaven is all a mistake. We are all in heaven; and the Lord’s prayer, according to this foggy theology simply means, Our Father which art everywhere, hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come, thy will be done, on earth, as it is everywhere.</p>

<p>Again, Bible readers have believed that Enoch and Elijah were really taken up to God in heaven. But if God and heaven be as much in every place as in any one place, this is all a mistake. They were not translated. And all that is said about the chariot of fire, and horses of fire, and the attending whirlwind to take Elijah up into heaven, was a useless parade. They only evaporated, and a misty vapor passed through the entire universe. This is all of Enoch and Elijah that the mind can possibly grasp, admitting that God and heaven are no more in any one place than in every place. But it is said of Elijah that he “went up by a whirlwind into heaven.” 2 Kings 2:11. And of Enoch it is said that he “walked with God, and was not, for God took him.” Genesis 5:24.</p>

<p>Jesus is said to be on the right hand of the Majesty on high.” Hebrews 1:3. “So, then, after the Lord had spoken unto them he was received up into heaven, and sat on the right hand of God.” Mark 16:19. But if heaven be everywhere, and God everywhere, then Christ’s ascension up to heaven, at the Father’s right hand, simply means that he went everywhere! He was only taken up where the cloud hid him from the gaze of his disciples, and then evaporated and went everywhere! So that instead of the lovely Jesus, so beautifully described in both Testaments, we have only a sort of essence dispersed through the entire universe. And in harmony with this rarified theology, Christ’s second advent, or his return, would be the condensation of this essence to some locality, say the mount of Olivet! Christ arose from the dead with a physical form. “He is not here,” said the angel, “for he is risen as he said.” Matthew 28:6.</p>

<p>“And as they went to tell his disciples, behold, Jesus met them, saying, All hail! And they came and held him by the <em>feet</em>, and they worshiped him.” Verse 9.</p>

<p>“Behold my <em>hands</em> and my <em>feet</em>,” said Jesus to those who stood in doubt of his resurrection, “that it is I myself. Handle me and see, for a spirit hath not flesh and bones as ye see me have. And when he had thus spoken, he showed them his hands and his feet. And while they yet believed not for joy, and wondered, he said unto them, Have ye here any meat? And they gave him a piece of broiled fish, and of an honey-comb, and he took it and did eat before them.” Luke 24:39-43.</p>

<p>After Jesus addressed his disciples on the mount of Olivet, he was taken up from them, and a cloud received him out of their sight. “And while they looked steadfastly toward heaven as he went up, behold two men stood by them in white apparel, which also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? This same Jesus which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven.” Acts 1:9-11. J. W.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Onang’o</name></author><category term="godhead" /><category term="trinity" /><category term="pioneers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MAN was made in the image of God. “And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness.” “So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him.” Genesis 1:26, 27. See also chap. 9:6; 1 Corinthians 11:7. Those who deny the personality of God, say that “image” here does not mean physical form, but moral image, and they make this the grand starting point to prove the immortality of all men. The argument stands thus: First, man was made in God’s moral image. Second, God is an immortal being. Third, therefore all men are immortal. But this mode of reasoning would also prove man omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent, and thus clothe mortal man with all the attributes of the deity. Let us try it: First, man was made in God’s moral image. Second, God is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. Third, therefore, man is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. That which proves too much, proves nothing to the point, therefore the position that the image of God means his moral image, cannot be sustained. As proof that God is a person, read his own words to Moses: “And the Lord said, Behold there is a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon a rock; and it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a cleft of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand while I pass by. And I will take away mine hand and thou shalt see my back parts; but my face shall not be seen.” Exodus 33:21-23. See also chap. 24:9-11. Here God tells Moses that he shall see his form. To say that God made it appear to Moses that he saw his form, when he has no form, is charging God with adding to falsehood a sort of juggling deception upon his servant Moses.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personality of God</title><link href="/2023/05/05/Personality-of-God.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personality of God" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/05/Personality-of-God</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/05/Personality-of-God.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="personality-of-god">Personality of God</h1>

<p>MAN was made in the image of God. “And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness.” “So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him.” Genesis 1:26, 27. See also chap. 9:6; 1 Corinthians 11:7. Those who deny the personality of God, say that “image” here does not mean physical form, but moral image, and they make this the grand starting point to prove the immortality of all men. The argument stands thus: First, man was made in God’s moral image. Second, God is an immortal being. Third, therefore all men are immortal. But this mode of reasoning would also prove man omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent, and thus clothe mortal man with all the attributes of the deity. Let us try it: First, man was made in God’s moral image. Second, God is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. Third, therefore, man is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. That which proves too much, proves nothing to the point, therefore the position that the image of God means his moral image, cannot be sustained. As proof that God is a person, read his own words to Moses: “And the Lord said, Behold there is a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon a rock; and it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a cleft of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand while I pass by. And I will take away mine hand and thou shalt see my back parts; but my face shall not be seen.” Exodus 33:21-23. See also chap. 24:9-11. Here God tells Moses that he shall see his form. To say that God made it appear to Moses that he saw his form, when he has no form, is charging God with adding to falsehood a sort of juggling deception upon his servant Moses.</p>

<p>But the skeptic thinks he sees a contradiction between verse 11, which says that the Lord spake unto Moses face to face, and verse 20, which states that Moses could not see his face. But let Numbers 12:5-8 remove the difficulty. “And the Lord came down in the pillar of the cloud, and stood in the door of the tabernacle, and called Aaron and Miriam, and they both came forth. And he said, Hear now my words. If there be a prophet among you, I, the Lord, will make myself known unto him in a vision, and will speak unto him in a dream. My servant Moses is not so, who is faithful in all mine house. With him will I speak mouth to mouth, <em>even apparently</em>.”</p>

<p>The great and dreadful God came down, wrapped in a cloud of glory. This cloud could be seen, but not the face which possesses more dazzling brightness than a thousand suns. Under these circumstances Moses was permitted to draw near and converse with God face to face, or mouth to mouth, <em>even apparently</em>.</p>

<p>Says the prophet Daniel, “I beheld till the thrones were cast down, and the Ancient of days did sit, whose garment was white as snow, and the hairs of his head like the pure wool; his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheels as burning fire.” Chap. 7:9. “I saw in the night visions, and, behold, one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of days, and they brought him near before him, and there was given him dominion and glory and a kingdom.” Verses 13, 14.</p>

<p>Here is a sublime description of the action of two personages; viz, God the Father, and his Son Jesus Christ. Deny their personality, and there is not a distinct idea in these quotations from Daniel. In connection with this quotation read the apostle’s declaration that the Son was in the express image of his Father’s person. “God, who at sundry times, and in divers manners, spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets, hath in these last days spoken unto us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by whom also he made the worlds; who being the brightness of his glory, and the <em>express image of his person</em>.” Hebrews 1:1-3.</p>

<p>We here add the testimony of Christ. “And the Father himself which hath sent me, hath borne witness of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his <em>shape</em>.” John 5:37. See also Philippians 2:6. To say that the Father has not a personal shape, seems the most pointed contradiction of plain scripture terms. OBJECTION. — “God is a Spirit.” John 4:24.</p>

<p>ANSWER. — Angels are also spirits [Psalm 104:4], yet those that visited Abram and Lot, lay down, ate, and took hold of Lot’s hand. They were spirit beings. So is God a Spirit being.</p>

<p>OBJ. — God is everywhere. Proof. Psalm 139:1-8. He is as much in every place as in any one place.</p>

<p>ANS. — 1. God is everywhere by virtue of his omniscience, as will be seen by the very words of David referred to above. Verses 1-6. “O Lord, thou hast searched me, and known me. Thou knowest my down-sitting and mine uprising; thou understandest my thought afar off. Thou compassest my path and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways. For there is not a word in my tongue, but, lo, O Lord, thou knowest it altogether. Thou hast beset me behind and before, and laid thy hand upon me. Such knowledge is too wonderful for me. It is high; I cannot attain unto it.”</p>

<p>2. God is everywhere by virtue of his Spirit, which is his representative, and is manifested wherever he pleases, as will be seen by the very words the objector claims, referred to above. Verses 7-10. “Whither shall I go from thy Spirit? or whither shall I flee from thy presence? If I ascend up into heaven, thou art there; if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou art there. If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea, even there shall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand shall hold me.”</p>

<p>God is in heaven. This we are taught in the Lord’s prayer. “Our Father which art in heaven.” Matthew 6:9; Luke 11:2. But if God is as much in every place as he is in any one place, then heaven is also as much in every place as it is in any one place, and the idea of going to heaven is all a mistake. We are all in heaven; and the Lord’s prayer, according to this foggy theology simply means, Our Father which art everywhere, hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come, thy will be done, on earth, as it is everywhere.</p>

<p>Again, Bible readers have believed that Enoch and Elijah were really taken up to God in heaven. But if God and heaven be as much in every place as in any one place, this is all a mistake. They were not translated. And all that is said about the chariot of fire, and horses of fire, and the attending whirlwind to take Elijah up into heaven, was a useless parade. They only evaporated, and a misty vapor passed through the entire universe. This is all of Enoch and Elijah that the mind can possibly grasp, admitting that God and heaven are no more in any one place than in every place. But it is said of Elijah that he “went up by a whirlwind into heaven.” 2 Kings 2:11. And of Enoch it is said that he “walked with God, and was not, for God took him.” Genesis 5:24.</p>

<p>Jesus is said to be on the right hand of the Majesty on high.” Hebrews 1:3. “So, then, after the Lord had spoken unto them he was received up into heaven, and sat on the right hand of God.” Mark 16:19. But if heaven be everywhere, and God everywhere, then Christ’s ascension up to heaven, at the Father’s right hand, simply means that he went everywhere! He was only taken up where the cloud hid him from the gaze of his disciples, and then evaporated and went everywhere! So that instead of the lovely Jesus, so beautifully described in both Testaments, we have only a sort of essence dispersed through the entire universe. And in harmony with this rarified theology, Christ’s second advent, or his return, would be the condensation of this essence to some locality, say the mount of Olivet! Christ arose from the dead with a physical form. “He is not here,” said the angel, “for he is risen as he said.” Matthew 28:6.</p>

<p>“And as they went to tell his disciples, behold, Jesus met them, saying, All hail! And they came and held him by the <em>feet</em>, and they worshiped him.” Verse 9.</p>

<p>“Behold my <em>hands</em> and my <em>feet</em>,” said Jesus to those who stood in doubt of his resurrection, “that it is I myself. Handle me and see, for a spirit hath not flesh and bones as ye see me have. And when he had thus spoken, he showed them his hands and his feet. And while they yet believed not for joy, and wondered, he said unto them, Have ye here any meat? And they gave him a piece of broiled fish, and of an honey-comb, and he took it and did eat before them.” Luke 24:39-43.</p>

<p>After Jesus addressed his disciples on the mount of Olivet, he was taken up from them, and a cloud received him out of their sight. “And while they looked steadfastly toward heaven as he went up, behold two men stood by them in white apparel, which also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? This same Jesus which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven.” Acts 1:9-11. J. W.</p>]]></content><author><name>James White</name></author><category term="godhead" /><category term="trinity" /><category term="pioneers" /><category term="extras" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Personality of God]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Untitleddocument</title><link href="/2023/05/05/Untitleddocument.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Untitleddocument" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/05/Untitleddocument</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/05/Untitleddocument.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="se">\#</span><span class="s2">{name}"</span>

<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="nb">print</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="p">\</span><span class="c1">#=\&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the [Jekyll docs][jekyll-docs] for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at [Jekyll’s GitHub repo][jekyll-gh]. If you have questions, you can ask them on [Jekyll Talk][jekyll-talk].</p>

<p>[jekyll-docs]: https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home</p>

<p>[jekyll-gh]: https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll</p>

<p>[jekyll-talk]: https://talk.jekyllrb.com/</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your \_posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About</title><link href="/2023/05/05/about-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/05/about-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/05/about-us.html"><![CDATA[<p>Victory Everlasting Gospel Ministry (VEGM) is a Seventh-day Adventist ministry that was founded in 2010 in Kenya. Since its inception, VEGM has grown to become a prominent religious organization in the country, with a network of churches and other institutions.</p>

<p>The primary objective of VEGM is to spread the Gospel of Jesus Christ and to provide spiritual guidance and support to individuals and communities. The ministry is founded on the belief that through faith, people can experience healing, deliverance, and transformation. As a result, VEGM places a great emphasis on prayer, Bible study, and evangelism.</p>

<h1 id="publishing">Publishing</h1>

<p>VEGM operates several churches across Kenya, with each church being led by a pastor and a team of elders. The ministry’s pastors are trained to deliver sermons that are grounded in biblical teachings and relevant to the everyday lives of their congregants. In addition to church services, VEGM organizes retreats, seminars, and workshops to help members deepen their faith and understanding of God’s word.</p>

<p>Aside from religious services, VEGM also runs several institutions, including a primary school, a secondary school, and a health center. These institutions are designed to provide quality education and healthcare to members of the community, regardless of their religious affiliation. The primary and secondary schools offer a holistic education that integrates Christian values, while the health center provides medical care and counseling services.</p>

<p>One of the unique features of VEGM is that it offers its facilities to other ministries to host events. This gesture is a testament to the ministry’s commitment to promoting unity among Christians and fostering a sense of community. Churches and other organizations can book VEGM’s facilities to host conferences, seminars, and other events.</p>

<h1 id="sanitarium">Sanitarium</h1>

<p>In conclusion, Victory Everlasting Gospel Ministry is a prominent Seventh-day Adventist ministry in Kenya. Its commitment to spreading the Gospel and providing support to individuals and communities has seen it grow into a network of churches and institutions. VEGM’s emphasis on prayer, Bible study, and evangelism is a testament to its dedication to helping people deepen their faith and understanding of God’s word.</p>

<h1 id="agriculture">Agriculture</h1>

<p>Something also here on agricultural work</p>

<h1 id="other-ministries">Other Ministries</h1>

<p>Something also here on other mnistries</p>]]></content><author><name>James White</name></author><category term="godhead" /><category term="trinity" /><category term="pioneers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Victory Everlasting Gospel Ministry (VEGM) is a Seventh-day Adventist ministry that was founded in 2010 in Kenya. Since its inception, VEGM has grown to become a prominent religious organization in the country, with a network of churches and other institutions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Renamed_post</title><link href="/2023/05/05/renamed_post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renamed_post" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/05/renamed_post</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/05/renamed_post.html"><![CDATA[<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Layout</th>
      <th>Main</th>
      <th> </th>
      <th> </th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Author</td>
      <td>Anon</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>navBar</td>
      <td>navBarNoHero</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This is the third post that I want to put into the website. It has been renamed/moved.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/posts/2023-05-05-renamed_post/media/image1.png" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Layout Main     Author Anon     navBar navBarNoHero    ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome To Jekyll</title><link href="/2023/05/05/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome To Jekyll" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/05/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/05/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/posts/2023-05-05-welcome-to-jekyll/media/image1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="se">\#</span><span class="s2">{name}"</span>

<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="nb">print</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="p">\</span><span class="c1">#=\&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the [Jekyll docs][jekyll-docs] for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at [Jekyll’s GitHub repo][jekyll-gh]. If you have questions, you can ask them on [Jekyll Talk][jekyll-talk].</p>

<p>[jekyll-docs]: https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home</p>

<p>[jekyll-gh]: https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll</p>

<p>[jekyll-talk]: https://talk.jekyllrb.com/</p>

<p># ![](/media/image1.png){width=”1.5052088801399826in” height=”0.4456758530183727in”}</p>

<p>P.O. Box 30439-00100</p>

<p>Nairobi, Kenya</p>

<p>tel. +254 713 234 798</p>

<p>[March 7th, 2018]{.underline}</p>

<p>**To Whom it May Concern:**</p>

<p>Dear Sir/Madam,</p>

<p><strong><em><span class="underline">RE: ENG. BRIAN ONANG’O</span></em></strong></p>

<p>This is to certify that Eng. Brian Odhiambo Onang’o has been working at</p>

<p>our organization as a Mechatronics Engineer since August 21st, 2016.</p>

<p>Yours sincerely,</p>

<p>Mark de Blois</p>

<p>CEO/Founder</p>

<p>![](/assets/img/posts/2023-05-05-welcome-to-jekyll/media/image1.png){width=”8.454679571303586in”</p>

<p>height=”12.177083333333334in”}</p>

<p>**Sabbath School Lessons**</p>

<p>**For**</p>

<p>**Senior Classes**</p>

<p>**The Second Epistle of Peter**</p>

<p>**March – June 2021**</p>

<p>![C:\Users\Verah\Pictures\first</p>

<p>Angel\_.jpg](/media/image2.jpeg){width=”1.9069444444444446in”</p>

<p>height=”1.5993055555555555in”}</p>

<p>**GOSPEL SOUNDERS PUBLICATIONS**</p>

<p>Copyright © 2021, Gospel Sounders Publications</p>

<p>Published by Gospel Sounders Publications</p>

<p>Web site: https://sabbathschool.gospelsounders.org</p>

<p>Email: editor@gospelsounders.org</p>

<p>Phone: +254 706662011</p>

<p>GOSPEL SOUNDERS seeks to interest men, by pen and voice, in moral and</p>

<p>spiritual reading. This can only be done on the basis of the Bible,</p>

<p>which alone is the sufficient rule of faith and practice and the test of</p>

<p>all doctrine. The intent is to lead men away from the traditions and</p>

<p>speculative and spiritualistic teachings of their churches to the pure</p>

<p>truths of the Bible; to lead them far away from fanatical dependence on</p>

<p>that failing arm of flesh of the Pharisees of our day – the corrupt</p>

<p>theologians – to the unfailing fountain of truth, even the Truth</p>

<p>Himself; and to show that God has endowed the dumbest man with</p>

<p>sufficient ability to study for himself and understand for himself the</p>

<p>sanctifying Word of God.</p>

<p>TO ORDER:</p>

<p>For your own copy of *Sabbath School Lesson* or for additional copies or</p>

<p>for other books, visit gs-publications.org, or send an email to:</p>

<p>editor@gospelsounders.org</p>

<p>## **Contents**</p>

<p>[Contents [i](#contents)](#contents)</p>

<p>Introduction ii</p>

<p>[1– The Christian Experience of Simon Peter –</p>

<p>*March…………………..*[1](#_Toc68179989)](#_Toc68179989)</p>

<p>2 -- Partaking The Divine Nature – *March</p>

<p>13…………………………….3*</p>

<p>3 -- The Christian Ladder – *March</p>

<p>20*………….……………………….6</p>

<p>[4 – Christian Love – *March</p>

<p>2*](#lesson-4-christian-love)…………………………………………..9</p>

<p>[5 –Making Your Calling and Election Sure – *April</p>

<p>3*](#lesson-5-making-your-calling-and-election-sure)……………….…12</p>

<p>[6 – Peter’s Witness and The Sure Word – *April</p>

<p>10*](#lesson-6-peters-witness-and-the-sure-word)……………………14</p>

<p>[7 – Warnings and Safety Measures – *April</p>

<p>17*](#lesson-7-warnings-and-safety-measures.)……………………….…17</p>

<p>[8 -- Warnings and Safety Measures (Continued) – *April</p>

<p>24*](#lesson-8—warnings-and-safety-measures-continued)…………...19</p>

<p>[9 – Surety of The Lord’s Promises – *May</p>

<p>1*](#lesson-8—warnings-and-safety-measures-continued)……………………………21</p>

<p>[10 --The Coming of the Lord – *May</p>

<p>8*](#lesson-10–the-coming-of-the-lord)………………………………….24</p>

<p>[11 -- Carefulness in The Christian Walk – *May</p>

<p>1*](#lesson-11-carefulness-in-the-christian-walk-as-the-end-draws-near)5……………………..25</p>

<p>[12 – Can We Know the Time? – *May</p>

<p>22*………………………………..27](#lesson-12-can-we-know-the-time)</p>

<p>[13 – Health and Temperance – *May</p>

<p>29*](#lesson-13-health-and-temperance)………………………………….29</p>

<p>[14 – Sabbath Keeping – *June</p>

<p>5*](#lesson-14-sabbath-keeping.)………………………………………….31</p>

<p>[15 – Christian Education – *June</p>

<p>12*.](#lesson-15-christian-education.).......................................................…33</p>

<p>[16 –](#lesson-16-the-christian-home) The Christian Home -- *June</p>

<p>19..*…………………………………...36</p>

<p>[17– Christian Character – *June</p>

<p>26*](#_Toc68180005)............................................................39</p>

<p>**\</p>

<p>**</p>

<p>**Introductory Note**</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p>The study of these Sabbath school lessons will give you a longing for</p>

<p>help in developing a deeper Christian experience. This should call for</p>

<p>the clear and impressive explanations of the principles of truth, and</p>

<p>God's plan for you, as given in the volumes of Mrs. E. G. White.</p>

<p>Without them, a Seventh-day Adventist home library is incomplete.</p>

<p>Leaders among these are:</p>

<p>TESTIMONIES FOR THE CHURCH</p>

<p>(4 volumes)</p>

<p>PATRIARCHS AND PROPHETS</p>

<p>PROPHETS AND KINGS</p>

<p>DESIRE OF AGES</p>

<p>ACTS OF THE APOSTLES</p>

<p>GREAT CONTROVERSY</p>

<p>STEPS TO CHRIST</p>

<p>CHRIST'S OBJECT LESSONS</p>

<p>EDUCATION</p>

<p>MINISTRY OF HEALING.</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 1 – The Christian Experience of Simon Peter</p>

<p>MARCH 6, 2021</p>

<p>Study Helps: Acts of the Apostles, Chapters 51 &amp; 52.</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. The author</p>

<pre><code class="language-{=html}">
\&lt;\!-- --\&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>a. Who wrote the epistle? Note 1.</p>

<p>b. Why is it important for us to understand this? Note 2.</p>

<p>c. Is the understanding of the author’s absolutely important to the</p>

<p>understanding of scripture? See Joel 1:1,2. Compare Jeremiah 1:1-3.</p>

<p>d. Whose words does he say are inspired? 2 Peter 1:21.</p>

<p>e. Are his words any less important than those of a prophet? 2 Peter</p>

<p>3:1-2.</p>

<pre><code class="language-{=html}">
\&lt;\!-- --\&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>2. How does he describe himself in the first epistle, how in the</p>

<p>second?</p>

<p>3. What do these modes of naming himself seem to suggest?</p>

<p>&gt; *Consider that the second epistle is written shortly before his death.</p>

<p>&gt; See 2 Peter 1: 14*</p>

<p>4. What has his birth name? Acts 15:14, John 1:41-42.</p>

<p>5. How did he get the name? Verse 42.</p>

<p>6. What is the meaning of the name? Verse 42</p>

<p>7. What incident occurred early in Simon’s acquaintance with Jesus?</p>

<p>Luke 15:1- 11.</p>

<p>8. What was his first step in Christian experience? Verses 5, 8, 11.</p>

<p>*Ans: -*</p>

<pre><code class="language-{=html}">
\&lt;\!-- --\&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>a. Nevertheless at thy word. Compare *Jeremiah 38:14-26; 42:2-5,19-22*.</p>

<p>b. I am a sinful man.</p>

<p>c. Forsook all and followed him.</p>

<pre><code class="language-{=html}">
\&lt;\!-- --\&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>9. What strong stand for Christ did Peter take later, when men were</p>

<p>doubting Him? Matt. 16: 13-16.</p>

<pre><code class="language-{=html}">
\&lt;\!-- --\&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>a. Through what does he say we may receive grace and peace?</p>

<p>b. Through what have we received all things that \[pertain\] unto life</p>

<p>and godliness? 2 Peter 1:3.</p>

<p>c. How will we be in this knowledge if we do not advance in the</p>

<p>Christian life? 2 Peter 1:8.</p>

<pre><code class="language-{=html}">
\&lt;\!-- --\&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>10. How did Jesus respond? Matt. 16:17.</p>

<p>11. Was Peter yet fully the Lord’s? See verse 23.</p>

<p>12. What special privilege did Peter enjoy soon afterward? Matt. 17:1-5.</p>

<p>13. What did Jesus say to Peter long afterward? Luke 22:31.</p>

<p>14. Was Peter yet fully converted? Verse 32. Note 3.</p>

<p>15. How did Peter respond to the Lord’s assurance that Satan should not</p>

<p>have him? Verse 33.</p>

<p>16. How did Jesus warn Peter after this confident declaration? Verse 34.</p>

<p>17. In what gentle way did the Lord rebuke Peter after his third denial?</p>

<p>Verse 61.</p>

<p>18. How did this affect Peter? Verse 62.</p>

<p>19. What threefold question did Jesus ask Peter after the resurrection?</p>

<p>What threefold commission did He give him? John 21:15-17.</p>

<p>20. What were Jesus’ last recorded words to Peter? Verse 22, last part.</p>

<p>21. What had been among His first words to Peter? Matt. 4:18, 19.</p>

<p>22. Mention some instances which show that Peter heeded his Master’s</p>

<p>bidding. See Acts 2-5, 10, 12.</p>

<p>23. What could Peter, out, of a full experience, exhort believers to</p>

<p>account salvation? 2 Peter 3:15, first part. Note 4.</p>

<p>24. Why does the Lord exercise long-suffering to all, as He did to</p>

<p>Peter? Verse 9.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. Observe in all the epistles of the New Testament, except those of</p>

<p>John, the custom of the writer’s announcing his identity at the</p>

<p>beginning of the epistle rather than at the close, as we do now.</p>

<p>Even John does the same in the book of Revelation.</p>

<p>2. Let us in imagination go back to that scene, and, as we sit with the</p>

<p>disciples on the mountainside, enter into the thoughts and feelings</p>

<p>that filled their hearts. Understanding what the words of Jesus</p>

<p>meant to those who heard them, we may discern in them a new</p>

<p>vividness and beauty, and may also gather for ourselves their deeper</p>

<p>lessons. – *Thoughts from the Mount of Blessing, pp. 1.2.*</p>

<p>3. It was after Peter had been led to self-renunciation and entire</p>

<p>reliance upon divine power, that he received his call to act as an</p>

<p>undershepherd. Christ had said to Peter, before his denial of Him,</p>

<p>“When thou art converted, strengthen thy brethren.” Luke 22:32.</p>

<p>These words were significant of the wide and effectual work which</p>

<p>this apostle was to do in the future for those who should come to</p>

<p>the faith. For this work, Peter’s own experience of sin and</p>

<p>suffering and repentance had prepared him. Not until he had learned</p>

<p>his weakness, could he know the believer’s need of dependence on</p>

<p>Christ. Amid the storm of temptation he had come to understand that</p>

<p>man can walk safely only as in utter self-distrust he relies upon</p>

<p>the Saviour. – *Acts of the Apostles, pp. 515.1.*</p>

<p>4. As time went on, the apostle’s influence as an educator and leader</p>

<p>increased; and while he never lost his burden to labor especially</p>

<p>for the Jews, yet he bore his testimony in many lands and</p>

<p>strengthened the faith of multitudes in the gospel. – *Ibid., pp.</p>

<p>516.4.*</p>

<p>The Saviour’s manner of dealing with Peter had a lesson for him and his</p>

<p>brethren. Although Peter had denied his Lord, the love which Jesus bore</p>

<p>him had never faltered. And as the apostle should take up the work of</p>

<p>ministering the word to others, he was to meet the transgressor with</p>

<p>patience, sympathy, and forgiving love. Remembering his own weakness and</p>

<p>failure, he was to deal with the sheep and lambs committed to his care</p>

<p>as tenderly as Christ had dealt with him. – *Ibid., pp. 516.2.*</p>

<p>Human beings, themselves given to evil, are prone to deal untenderly</p>

<p>with the tempted and the erring. They cannot read the heart; they know</p>

<p>not its struggle and its pain. Of the rebuke that is love, of the blow</p>

<p>that wounds to heal, of the warning that speaks hope, they have need to</p>

<p>learn. – *Ibid., pp. AA 516.*</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 2 – Partaking the Divine Nature</p>

<p>MARCH 13, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:1-4</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. What are the two key words to the second epistle of Peter? 2 Peter</p>

<p>3: 17, 18. Note 1.</p>

<p>2. What is the theme of chapter 1 in Peter’s second epistle? Note 2.</p>

<p>*Answer: Christian growth, or “the development of Christian character”</p>

<p>– AA 529.1, or “Christian progress” – AA 530.1. (Read the chapter</p>

<p>through, noting the terms “multiplied,” “add,” “beside this,” “abound,”</p>

<p>“give diligence.”)*</p>

<p>3. What is the surest means of Christian growth and of protection</p>

<p>against being deceived by false teachings? 2 Peter 3: 2; 3:17; 1:10.</p>

<p>Note 3.</p>

<p>4. To whom did Peter address his second epistle? Verse 1.</p>

<p>5. How is this “precious faith” obtained? Ib., last part. Note 4.</p>

<p>6. What invocation did the apostle make in behalf of those whom he</p>

<p>addressed? Verse 2.</p>

<p>7. How are grace and peace multiplied? Verse 2. Note 5.</p>

<p>8. What does grace do for those who accept it? Heb. 4:16; 2 Cor. 12:9;</p>

<p>Titus 2:11.</p>

<p>9. Who alone have peace? Rom. 5:1; Isa. 48:18; 57:20, 21.</p>

<p>10. Then to what, in effect, is Peter’s invocation in verse 2</p>

<p>equivalent? Phil. 1:9-11.</p>

<p>11. How are this grace and peace to be obtained? 2 Peter 1:2.</p>

<p>12. How much of that which is needful to the acquirement of life and</p>

<p>godliness has God given to us? Verse 3.</p>

<p>13. What is the measure of experimental knowledge God would have us</p>

<p>gain? Verse 3. Note 6.</p>

<p>*Answer: “His divine power . . . through the knowledge of Him that hath</p>

<p>called us.”*</p>

<p>14. What is the twofold object of these wonderful gifts of divine power</p>

<p>and precious promises? Verse 4.</p>

<p>15. How much does the apostle Paul say that God will do for us? Eph.</p>

<p>3:20.</p>

<p>16. How is this aid brought to us? 2 Peter 1:3, last part.</p>

<p>17. What else is given by his divine power? Verse 4, first part.</p>

<p>18. What may we gain by these “exceeding great and precious promises”?</p>

<p>19. What must we escape, in order to be made partakers of the divine</p>

<p>nature?</p>

<p>20. Mention the greatest of these exceeding great and precious promises?</p>

<p>2 Cor. 6:17, 18.</p>

<p>21. What does Paul say that we should do, in view of these promises? 2</p>

<p>Cor. 7:1.</p>

<p>22. Having become sons of God, what other promise necessarily follows?</p>

<p>Rom. 8:16, 17; 1 John 3:2.</p>

<p>23. What must follow if a man really has this hope in him? 1 John 3:3.</p>

<p>24. What is “the corruption that is in the world through lust”? 1 John</p>

<p>2:15, 16; Matt. 15:19, 20.</p>

<p>25. Then what change must take place to constitute one a “partaker of</p>

<p>the divine nature,” a son of God? Ps. 51:10; Eze. 36:26, 27.</p>

<p>26. What encouragement may we gain from a contemplation of the glory of</p>

<p>God, which he will bestow upon his children? Eph. 3:16.</p>

<p>27. Then how greatly may grace and peace be multiplied to us “through</p>

<p>the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord”? Verses 16-19.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. In Peter’s own summary at the conclusion of this epistle are clearly</p>

<p>seen the key words to the twofold burden that called it forth:</p>

<p>“beware” and “grow”; in other words, warning and exhortation.</p>

<p>2. Peter’s Christian experience had been an intense one. More than any</p>

<p>other of the disciples, perhaps, he had gone to the extreme of</p>

<p>failure at the crisis of his Master’s humiliation. Now that his work</p>

<p>is about done, Peter feels especially anxious that after his death</p>

<p>the believers shall continue to grow in experimental knowledge of</p>

<p>God.</p>

<p>3. In 2 Peter 3: 2, Peter sums up what he has amplified in chapter 1 –</p>

<p>that the means of Christian growth is the diligent study of the</p>

<p>Word, both prophetic and practical, in order to keep fresh in mind</p>

<p>the “exceeding great and precious promises” (2 Peter 1:4), making</p>

<p>them a basis for cultivating the Christian virtues.</p>

<p>4. The marginal rendering of verse 1, the rendering given in the</p>

<p>Revised Version, more nearly conforms to the Greek than does the</p>

<p>text. While we may not use a marginal rendering as the basis of any</p>

<p>doctrine, the absolute divinity of Christ is so well established by</p>

<p>other scriptures, that we know that he is justly entitled to be</p>

<p>called God as well as Saviour. For instance, Isaiah says of the Son</p>

<p>to be given, that “his name shall be called Wonderful, Counselor,</p>

<p>The mighty God, The everlasting Father, The Prince of Peace.” Isa.</p>

<p>9:6. John says: “In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was</p>

<p>with God, and the Word was God.” “And the Word was made flesh, and</p>

<p>dwelt among us.” John 1:1, 14. God the Father addresses the Son as</p>

<p>follows: “Thy throne, O God, is forever and ever.” Heb. 1:8. And</p>

<p>when the redeemed shall see Jesus their Saviour coming in the clouds</p>

<p>of heaven, they will say, “Lo, this is our God; we have waited for</p>

<p>him, and he will save us.” Isa. 25:9. Let none, therefore, find</p>

<p>fault with the rendering, Our God and Saviour Jesus Christ,” nor</p>

<p>fear to worship as God, Him whom all the angels are commanded to</p>

<p>worship.</p>

<p>It is the righteousness of God that forms the basis of faith, the most</p>

<p>precious possession of the believer.</p>

<p>5. As sons of God, it necessarily follows that our acquaintance with</p>

<p>him must become more and more intimate. It is this intimate</p>

<p>acquaintance with God which multiplies peace to us. “Acquaint now</p>

<p>thyself with him, and be at peace.” Job 22:21.</p>

<p>It is safe to say that the only reason there is a sinner in the world</p>

<p>to-day is because he does not know God and Jesus our Lord as he ought;</p>

<p>for really to know God and His Son Jesus, is declared to be eternal</p>

<p>life. John 17: 3. “My grace is sufficient for thee,” 2 Cor. 12:9</p>

<p>declared Jesus to Paul in a crisis of the latter’s experience —</p>

<p>sufficient for every need. The only way to grow in grace is to avail</p>

<p>ourselves of it every time we are under temptation or failure. The</p>

<p>experience of grace applied brings peace, and “grace upon grace” (John</p>

<p>1: 16, A. R. V., margin) leads on to “perfect peace” (Isa. 26: 3)</p>

<p>6. The stress which the apostle Peter lays upon a knowledge of God is</p>

<p>quite noticeable. Twice in this lesson it is mentioned. He would</p>

<p>evidently impress upon our minds the necessity of a personal</p>

<p>acquaintance with God - of knowing him as we would an intimate</p>

<p>friend - and of loving him not simply because of what he does, but</p>

<p>because of what he is. “God is love,” and “we love him because he</p>

<p>first loved us.” It is this perception of his character which first</p>

<p>draws us to him, - “the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance.”</p>

<p>Rom. 2:4. By this we are made partakers of the divine nature, that</p>

<p>is, adopted into the family of God.</p>

<p>In Gal. 4:6-9 the apostle Paul makes a knowledge of God equivalent to a</p>

<p>state of sonship. It is evident, therefore, that the knowledge of God,</p>

<p>of which the apostles speak, is far more than the simple knowledge and</p>

<p>belief that God exists as Creator of the world.</p>

<p>The word “knowledge” - *epignōsis* - used in verses 2 and 3 is a</p>

<p>compound of the simple form - *gnosis* - used in verses 5 and 6. It</p>

<p>denotes thorough knowledge, knowing a thing as it really is. It implies</p>

<p>expanding, added knowledge, and may properly be rendered here “knowledge</p>

<p>upon knowledge”, or as Strong has it, “full discernment” until it</p>

<p>includes “all things that pertain unto life and godliness.”</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 3 – The Christian Ladder</p>

<p>MARCH 20, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:5-7</p>

<p>*Study Helps: Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 52.*</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. What is done for us through the great promises of God? 2 Peter 1:4.</p>

<p>Note 1.</p>

<p>2. Because of this, what are we to do? Verses 5-7. Note 2.</p>

<p>3. What is the foundation of all graces? Verse 5.</p>

<p>4. Who gives us faith? Rom. 12:3.</p>

<p>5. What is the first thing that faith accomplishes for us? Rom. 5:1.</p>

<p>6. Being justified by faith, what do we become? Gal. 3:26.</p>

<p>7. What happens at what point a man gives up his faith? Note 3.</p>

<p>8. Having become children of God, may we settle down in</p>

<p>self-satisfaction? Eph. 5:1.</p>

<p>9. What must we do? Verse 2.</p>

<p>10. Whose example are we to follow? Verse 2; 1 John 2:6; 1 Peter 2:21.</p>

<p>11. Could we without faith do the things that God requires? Heb. 11:6;</p>

<p>Rom. 14:23, last part.</p>

<p>12. Having been justified, how alone can we remain in that state? Hab.</p>

<p>2:4.</p>

<p>13. What does true faith always do? Gal. 5:6, last clause.</p>

<p>14. How alone can faith be shown to be perfect? James 2:21, 22.</p>

<p>15. What is said of a faith from which no works proceed? James 2:17, 26.</p>

<p>16. What must we do to our faith? 2 Peter 1:5. Then upon what plan does</p>

<p>God require us to work? Upon what plan does He work? Verse 2. Note</p>

<p>4.</p>

<p>17. What is to be added to faith?</p>

<p>18. What is virtue? Note 5*.*</p>

<p>19. What it to be added to virtue?</p>

<p>20. What knowledge must be added? Col. 1:9, 10; Jer. 9:23-24.</p>

<p>21. What is the nature of this knowledge? James 3:17. Note 6.</p>

<p>22. What will be the result if we do not obtain this knowledge? Hosea</p>

<p>4:6, first clause.</p>

<p>23. What must be added to knowledge?</p>

<p>24. In what respect must we be temperate? 1 Cor. 9:25.</p>

<p>25. What is the meaning of temperance? *Ans. – Mastery of self;</p>

<p>self-control. See 1 Cor. 9:27*.</p>

<p>26. Does religion have anything to do with one’s eating and drinking? 1</p>

<p>Cor. 10:31.</p>

<p>27. If a man eats and drinks simply for the gratification of his</p>

<p>appetite, what does he worship? Phil. 3:18, 19.</p>

<p>28. What great commandment does he break? Ex. 20:3; Mark 12:29, 30. Note</p>

<p>7.</p>

<p>29. How are we to glorify God? 1 Cor. 6:20.</p>

<p>30. What will be the fate of those who give themselves up to indulgence</p>

<p>in appetite? Luke 21:34. What is surfeiting? See also Phil. 3:18,</p>

<p>19.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. Our Saviour is always ready to hear and answer the prayer of the</p>

<p>contrite heart, and grace and peace are multiplied to His faithful</p>

<p>ones. Gladly He grants them the blessings they need in their</p>

<p>struggle against the evils that beset them. – *Acts of the</p>

<p>Apostles, pp. 532.2.*</p>

<p>2. Having become partakers of the heavenly gift, they are to go on unto</p>

<p>perfection, being “kept by the power of God through faith.” 1 Peter</p>

<p>1:5. *– Ibid., pp. 530.2.*</p>

<p>“AND beside this giving all diligence, add to your faith,” etc. A</p>

<p>literal rendering of the words translated “and beside this,” would be,</p>

<p>“and for this cause,” which is equivalent to “wherefore.” (See SUV,</p>

<p>Williams, etc). The reference may be to the divine power that hath given</p>

<p>us all things that pertain unto life and godliness, or to the exceeding</p>

<p>great and precious promises, or to the divine nature of which we are</p>

<p>made partakers. Because of this power, because we are sons of God, we</p>

<p>should use all diligence to add the Christian graces.</p>

<p>THE idea of the apostle is not that anyone grace cannot be obtained</p>

<p>until the one preceding it has been perfected, as, for instance, that we</p>

<p>cannot have any godliness until we are perfect in faith, virtue,</p>

<p>knowledge, temperance, and patience; for all these things are a part of</p>

<p>godliness. But he means that *we should possess them all, and daily add</p>

<p>to each*. It may, however, be observed that there seems to be a definite</p>

<p>relation in point of order, especially between temperance and patience,</p>

<p>for it is utterly impossible for an intemperate man to be a patient man.</p>

<p>Indeed, temperance is, in a sense, patience, for temperance is</p>

<p>self-control, and patience is the controlling of one’s self under trying</p>

<p>circumstances. All the graces are, in fact, interwoven, but faith is the</p>

<p>foundation of all. It must precede every other good thing.</p>

<p>3. There are those who attempt to ascend the ladder of Christian</p>

<p>progress; but as they advance they begin to put their trust in the</p>

<p>power of man, and soon lose sight of Jesus, the Author and Finisher</p>

<p>of their faith. The result is failure--the loss of all that has</p>

<p>been gained. Sad indeed is the condition of those who, becoming</p>

<p>weary of the way, allow the enemy of souls to rob them of the</p>

<p>Christian graces that have been developing in their hearts and</p>

<p>lives. “He that lacketh these things,” declares the apostle, “is</p>

<p>blind, and cannot see afar off, and hath forgotten that he was</p>

<p>purged from his old sins.” *– Ibid., pp. 532.3*.</p>

<p>4. Day by day God labors for man’s sanctification, and man is to</p>

<p>co-operate with Him, putting forth persevering efforts in the</p>

<p>cultivation of right habits. He is to add grace to grace; and as he</p>

<p>thus works on the plan of addition, God works for him on the plan of</p>

<p>multiplication. Our Saviour is always ready to hear and answer the</p>

<p>prayer of the contrite heart, and grace and peace are multiplied to</p>

<p>His faithful ones. Gladly He grants them the blessings they need in</p>

<p>their struggle against the evils that beset them. *– Ibid., pp.*</p>

<p>*532.2.*</p>

<p>5. It is the glory of God to give His virtue to His children. *–</p>

<p>Ibid., pp. 530.2.* Having received the faith of the gospel, the next</p>

<p>work of the believer is to add to his character virtue, and thus</p>

<p>cleanse the heart and prepare the mind for the reception of the</p>

<p>knowledge of God. *– Ibid., pp. 530.3*.</p>

<p>On the word “virtue” Dr. Barnes says: - “The word here rendered virtue</p>

<p>is the same which is used in verse 3… All the things which the apostle</p>

<p>specifies, unless knowledge be an exception, are virtues in the sense in</p>

<p>which that word is commonly used, and it can hardly be supposed that the</p>

<p>apostle here meant to use a general term which would include all of the</p>

<p>others. The probability is, therefore, that by the word here he has</p>

<p>reference to the common meaning of the Greek word, as referring to</p>

<p>manliness, courage, vigor, energy; and the sense is that he wished them</p>

<p>to evince whatever firmness or courage might be necessary in maintaining</p>

<p>the principles of their religion, and in enduring the trials to which</p>

<p>their faith might be subjected. True virtue is not a tame and passive</p>

<p>thing. It requires great energy and boldness, for its very essence is</p>

<p>firmness, manliness, and independence.”</p>

<p>Clarke - Courage or fortitude, to enable you to profess the faith before</p>

<p>men, in these times of persecution.</p>

<p>1 Peter 2:9 – praises</p>

<p>Strong - Manliness, valor, excellence</p>

<p>6. This knowledge is the foundation of all true education and of all</p>

<p>true service. It is the only real safeguard against temptation; and</p>

<p>it is this alone that can make one like God in character. Through</p>

<p>the knowledge of God and of His Son Jesus Christ, are given to the</p>

<p>believer “all things that pertain unto life and godliness.” No good</p>

<p>gift is withheld from him who sincerely desires to obtain the</p>

<p>righteousness of God. – *Acts of the Apostle, pp. 530.3*. “This is</p>

<p>life eternal,” Christ said, “that they might know Thee the only true</p>

<p>God, and Jesus Christ, whom Thou hast sent.” John 17:3. And the</p>

<p>prophet Jeremiah declared: “Let not the wise man glory in his</p>

<p>wisdom, neither let the mighty man glory in his might, let not the</p>

<p>rich man glory in his riches: but let him that glorieth glory in</p>

<p>this, that he understandeth and knoweth Me, that I am the Lord which</p>

<p>exercise loving-kindness, judgment, and righteousness, in the earth:</p>

<p>for in these things I delight, saith the Lord.” Jeremiah 9:23, 24.</p>

<p>Scarcely can the human mind comprehend the breadth and depth and</p>

<p>height of the spiritual attainments of him who gains this knowledge.</p>

<p>*– Ibid., pp. 531.1.*</p>

<p>7. By a comparison of Phil. 3:19 and Ex. 20:3 we learn that</p>

<p>intemperance is a violation of the first commandment. But one who</p>

<p>violates the first commandment is an idolater. Therefore, it is</p>

<p>utterly impossible that an intemperate man should be a Christian. A</p>

<p>man who is given to surfeiting, has his mind so beclouded that he</p>

<p>cannot appreciate divine things, or if he dimly realizes them, he is</p>

<p>unable to give them his full attention, and so the great day of God</p>

<p>comes and finds him unprepared.</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 4 – Christian Love</p>

<p>MARCH 27, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:6-7</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. WHAT grace in Peter’s list follows next after temperance? 2 Peter</p>

<p>1:6.</p>

<p>2. How are we to inherit the promises of God? Heb. 6:11, 12.</p>

<p>3. How alone can we inherit eternal life? Rom. 2:7.</p>

<p>4. Under what circumstances must we be patient? Rom. 12:12.</p>

<p>5. What alone can produce patience? Rom. 5:3; James 1:2, 3.</p>

<p>6. If we are to glory in tribulation, and rejoice in the midst of</p>

<p>trials, what time shall we take for doubting, fears, and</p>

<p>discouragement? 1 Thess. 5:16; Phil. 4:4.</p>

<p>7. If we have the grace of patience in perfection, what shall we lack</p>

<p>that is necessary to a perfect character? James 1:4.</p>

<p>8. When trials shall have perfected patience in us, what will await us?</p>

<p>James 1:12; Heb. 10:36.</p>

<p>9. What does Peter mention next after patience?</p>

<p>10. What is declared to be “great gain”? 1 Tim. 6:6.</p>

<p>11. What follows godliness?</p>

<p>12. What commandment have we received that shows the fitness of saying</p>

<p>that brotherly kindness must be added to godliness? 1 John 4:21.</p>

<p>13. How alone may we know how we ought to love one another? 1 John</p>

<p>4:7-11.</p>

<p>14. What is the evidence that one has been converted? 1 John 3:14.</p>

<p>15. Is the measure of love that the new convert feels for the brethren</p>

<p>sufficient for all time? 1 Thess. 3:12; 4:9, 10.</p>

<p>16. How should we love one another? John 15:12; 13:34.</p>

<p>17. What is the greatest measure of love that a man can possess? John</p>

<p>15:13.</p>

<p>18. Ought we to love the brethren to that extent? 1 John 3:16.</p>

<p>19. What state of mind will render this less difficult than it would</p>

<p>naturally be? Phil. 2:3.</p>

<p>20. Repeat the apostle Paul’s specific description of perfect brotherly</p>

<p>kindness? Eph. 4:31, 32.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>&gt; “TRIBULATION worketh patience.” Nothing but tribulation can develop</p>

<p>&gt; patience. When everything goes smoothly, there is no call for</p>

<p>&gt; patience, and the person who has none can get along very well. And</p>

<p>&gt; when there is no demand for patience, it is certain that none can be</p>

<p>&gt; developed. Some people say that it is not true that tribulation works</p>

<p>&gt; patience; they say that trials and difficulties make them impatient.</p>

<p>&gt; But that is an error.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; It is impossible that trials should plant impatience in the heart. All</p>

<p>&gt; they do in the case of one who manifests ill-temper, is to bring to</p>

<p>&gt; light the fact that he is destitute of patience, and to develop</p>

<p>&gt; impatience into greater magnitude. But then why does his impatience</p>

<p>&gt; increase rather than diminish with the continuance of trials? Simply</p>

<p>&gt; because he has not the foundation upon which to build patience.</p>

<p>&gt; Without a groundwork of faith, it is impossible that tribulation</p>

<p>&gt; should work patience. And the Bible does not say that they will do so</p>

<p>&gt; under any other circumstances. See Rom. 5:1-5. But the one who has</p>

<p>&gt; firm faith will believe, and believing will realize that “all things</p>

<p>&gt; work together for good to them that love God,” and so he will gladly</p>

<p>&gt; endure trials.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; “AND we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.” This is</p>

<p>&gt; literally true, not of a few persons merely, but of all who are</p>

<p>&gt; followers of Christ, and not simply in times of persecution, but all</p>

<p>&gt; the time. This does not mean that we shall all or any of us be called</p>

<p>&gt; to go to the stake, the block, or the gallows for the brethren; it</p>

<p>&gt; means that our lives should be considered as not belonging to us, but</p>

<p>&gt; to the Lord, and that therefore they should be used in his service.</p>

<p>&gt; Christ is the great Example. He “went about doing good.” When he was</p>

<p>&gt; weary with toil, and faint with hunger, he found rest and refreshment</p>

<p>&gt; in laboring to lift up the fallen. He “pleased not himself.” He sought</p>

<p>&gt; only the welfare and pleasure of others. It is such service as this</p>

<p>&gt; that calls for self-denial of the same class as that which would lead</p>

<p>&gt; one actually to lay down his life for another. Without such a</p>

<p>&gt; self-sacrificing spirit as the ruling principle of one’s life, one</p>

<p>&gt; would not actually lay down his life for another, if it were required;</p>

<p>&gt; or if he should do so, the sacrifice would not be acceptable to God.</p>

<p>&gt; See 1 Cor. 13:3. Daily dying is the order with one who is a true</p>

<p>&gt; follower of Christ. This does not mean self-denial that is accompanied</p>

<p>&gt; by a wry face, it means service of which no one is cognizant –</p>

<p>&gt; necessary labor performed when weary, with the same cheerfulness as</p>

<p>&gt; when fresh. It is that quite service which finds its reward in the</p>

<p>&gt; fact that God knows.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; How may we esteem others better than ourselves? Easily enough; simply</p>

<p>&gt; by looking only at the good qualities of others, and by seeing</p>

<p>&gt; ourselves just as God sees us. The Holy Spirit, by means of its sword,</p>

<p>&gt; the word of God, lays bare our own deceitful hearts, and lets us see</p>

<p>&gt; them just as they appear to God. To be sure, for the sins that we find</p>

<p>&gt; there we may readily secure pardon; nevertheless having seen what</p>

<p>&gt; manner of actions our hearts naturally produce, and knowing that but</p>

<p>&gt; for the grace of God they would never produce any other, we should</p>

<p>&gt; learn humility. Now our brother may be in reality as bad as we, or</p>

<p>&gt; even worse; but since it is not given us to know the secrets of his</p>

<p>&gt; heart, the things which we can see in our own hearts – that is, the</p>

<p>&gt; evil passions which, if not repressed, would result in the wickedest</p>

<p>&gt; acts – are far worse than what we can see in our brother’s actions.</p>

<p>&gt; And so we can, in lowliness of mind, esteem others better than</p>

<p>&gt; ourselves.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; WITHOUT godliness, there can be no brotherly kindness. For (1) we must</p>

<p>&gt; first be adopted into the family of God before we can have brethren to</p>

<p>&gt; whom to exercise Christian kindness. And (2) it is from the love of</p>

<p>&gt; God that we learn to love one another; and we cannot know the love of</p>

<p>&gt; God except as it becomes a part of our being. Brotherly kindness is</p>

<p>&gt; simply the natural outflow of the love of God which is shed abroad in</p>

<p>&gt; our hearts by the Holy Spirit – that Spirit whose presence in us</p>

<p>&gt; marks us as children of God.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; THE measure of love which the newly converted man feels, is only a</p>

<p>&gt; sample of the love which he ought to feel after he has been a long</p>

<p>&gt; time in the way. Brotherly love which grows less after the beginning</p>

<p>&gt; of one’s Christian experience, is not such love as will give an</p>

<p>&gt; abundant entrance into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour</p>

<p>&gt; Jesus Christ. That is not an instance of progress toward Heaven, but</p>

<p>&gt; of having one’s feet set in the right way and then turning around and</p>

<p>&gt; going back toward the world. The Christian should “abound yet more and</p>

<p>&gt; more” in faith and love and every grace.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; Love is the basis of godliness. Whatever the profession, no man has</p>

<p>&gt; pure love to God unless he has unselfish love for his brother. But we</p>

<p>&gt; can never come into possession of this spirit by trying to love</p>

<p>&gt; others. What is needed is the love of Christ in the heart. When self</p>

<p>&gt; is merged in Christ, love springs forth spontaneously. The</p>

<p>&gt; completeness of Christian character is attained when the impulse to</p>

<p>&gt; help and bless others springs constantly from within--when the</p>

<p>&gt; sunshine of heaven fills the heart and is revealed in the countenance.</p>

<p>&gt; – *Christ’s Object Lessons, pp. 384.2.*</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 5 – Making Your Calling and Election Sure</p>

<p>APRIL 3, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1: 7-15</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. REPEAT the list of virtues sometimes called “Peter’s ladder”. 2</p>

<p>Peter 1:5-7.</p>

<p>2. What is the crowning grace? Verse 7, last part.</p>

<p>3. What is charity? Col. 3:14.</p>

<p>4. What other very common word is equivalent to charity? See Col. 3:14,</p>

<p>and other texts in Revised Version</p>

<p>5. What is the end or object of the commandment, or law, of God? I Tim.</p>

<p>1:5</p>

<p>6. What, indeed, is Bible charity or love? Rom. 13:10; 1 John 5:2, 3.</p>

<p>7. What is the Whole duty of man? Eccl. 12:13</p>

<p>8. Then since the keeping of the commandments is charity, how does</p>

<p>charity compare with the other graces? 1 Cor. 13:13.</p>

<p>9. Into how much of our actions should charity enter? 1 Cor. 16:14.</p>

<p>10. Without charity, what is the most eloquent man like? 1 Cor. 13:1.</p>

<p>11. Will-the possession of great faith and deep knowledge of the</p>

<p>mysteries of God, make up in any degree for lack of charity? Verse</p>

<p>2.</p>

<p>12. Show that charity does not consist simply in making great sacrifices</p>

<p>and giving to the poor. Verse 3.</p>

<p>13. Tell what are the characteristics of charity. Verses 4-6.</p>

<p>14. If all these graces abound in any person what will be his condition?</p>

<p>2 Peter 1:8.</p>

<p>15. Name some of the fruits that are equivalent to the above graces.</p>

<p>Gal. 5:22,23.</p>

<p>16. What is the condition of one who lacks these things? 2 Peter 1:9.</p>

<p>17. Then what should we do P Verse 10.</p>

<p>18. What glorious reward awaits those in whom “these things” abound?</p>

<p>Verse 11.</p>

<p>19. What must be the nature of those who inherit that eternal kingdom?</p>

<p>Titus 2:13, 14; Rev. 21:27.</p>

<p>20. Is the fact that we know these things any reason why we should not</p>

<p>study them diligently? 2 Peter 1:12.</p>

<p>21. Why was the apostle so zealous in stirring up the minds of the</p>

<p>people concerning these great truths? Verses 13, 14.</p>

<p>22. What had the Lord shown him concerning his death? John 21:18, 19.</p>

<p>23. What was Peter’s earnest desire that we should do? 2 Peter 1:15.</p>

<p>24. If these things are always in our mind, what prayer may we offer?</p>

<p>Ps. 5:1.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>&gt; CHARITY, or love, is “the bond of perfectness.” This may readily be</p>

<p>&gt; understood when we remember that “love is the fulfilling of the law,”</p>

<p>&gt; and that the whole law of God, including every duty that can be</p>

<p>&gt; required of man, is summed up in the two precepts, “Thou shalt love</p>

<p>&gt; the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with</p>

<p>&gt; all thy mind,” and, “Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself.” The</p>

<p>&gt; love which is the bond of perfectness is not a mere emotion, but is a</p>

<p>&gt; living, active principle, manifest in every deed and thought of one’s</p>

<p>&gt; life. Of course it is understood that love is the bond of perfectness</p>

<p>&gt; only when there is underlying faith, for faith works by love, and love</p>

<p>&gt; is the product of faith.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; “GIVE diligence, to make your calling and election sure.” Many are</p>

<p>&gt; called, but few are chosen. How many are called? All. Here is the</p>

<p>&gt; call: “Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, and he</p>

<p>&gt; that hath no money; come ye, buy, and eat; yea, come, buy wine and</p>

<p>&gt; milk without money and without price.” Isa. 55:1. “Whosoever will, let</p>

<p>&gt; him take the water of life freely.” Rev. 22:17. But not all will heed</p>

<p>&gt; the call; and of those who listen to it, very few comparatively will</p>

<p>&gt; gain the final inheritance, because the great majority will not</p>

<p>&gt; agonize to enter in. “Many, I say unto you, will seek to enter in, and</p>

<p>&gt; shall not be able.” Luke 13:24. A man may even be one of the elect, -</p>

<p>&gt; one of the specially loved of God, yet if he does not give diligence</p>

<p>&gt; to make his election sure, he will certainly fall. The doctrine of the</p>

<p>&gt; perseverance of the saints” is an excellent one, if the saints only</p>

<p>&gt; persevere; but they must not imagine that because they have tasted</p>

<p>&gt; that the Lord is precious, and have felt the power of the world to</p>

<p>&gt; come, therefore they are bound to be kept to the end, regardless of</p>

<p>&gt; their own actions. Only those who patiently continue in well-doing can</p>

<p>&gt; have eternal life. To each Christian the warning is given, “Hold that</p>

<p>&gt; fast which thou hast, that no man take thy crown.” Rev. 3:11.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; \<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 6 – Peter’s Witness and The Sure Word</p>

<p>APRIL 10, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:16-21</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. IN his second epistle, what does Peter say that he had previously</p>

<p>made known to the people? 2 Peter 1:16.</p>

<p>2. With what positiveness could Peter speak of the glory of Christ’s</p>

<p>coming? lb.</p>

<p>3. When had he been an eye-witness of Christ’s majesty as it will be</p>

<p>displayed at his second coming? Verses 17, 18.</p>

<p>4. State the details of this occurrence. Matt. 17:1-5; Mark. 9:2-8;</p>

<p>Luke 9:28-36.</p>

<p>5. What had Jesus previously said which also shows that the</p>

<p>transfiguration was a representation of the second coming of Christ?</p>

<p>Matt. 16:28; Mark 9:1.</p>

<p>6. Is it possible to have any better evidence than that given to Peter,</p>

<p>James, and John? 2 Peter 1:19.</p>

<p>7. What office does the word of prophecy serve to us? *Ib*. Ps.</p>

<p>119:105.</p>

<p>8. How long will it shine to show us the way? 2 Peter 1:19, last part.</p>

<p>9. In what period are we living, that a light should be necessary? Rom.</p>

<p>13:12; Isa. 60:2.</p>

<p>10. What has brought about this night of darkness? Rom. 1:21.</p>

<p>11. Who is the day-star? Rev. 22:16; John 8:12.</p>

<p>12. Can any prophecy be interpreted by the-unaided knowledge of any man?</p>

<p>2 Peter 1:20.</p>

<p>13. Why not? Verse 21.</p>

<p>14. *What connection has the light of prophecy with the day-star, the</p>

<p>light of the world? I Peter 1:10, 11.*</p>

<p>15. Why cannot all the world see this light? 1 Cor. 2:14; 2 Cor. 4:3, 4.</p>

<p>16. What aid must we have in order to understand it? 1 Cor. 2:9, 10.</p>

<p>17. Having the aid of the Spirit, how must we proceed in our study?</p>

<p>Verse 13, last clause.</p>

<p>&gt; **Notes**</p>

<p>IT is usually considered that one who was an eye-witness of any event is</p>

<p>the one best qualified to testify concerning it. And most certainly it</p>

<p>is better than testimony given at second hand. So Peter assures us that</p>

<p>he had not been deceived by cunningly devised fables when he made known</p>

<p>the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, because he himself had</p>

<p>been an eye-witness of his majesty. Then he refers to the</p>

<p>transfiguration scene, in a way to show that that was what he had in</p>

<p>mind as exhibiting the power and glory of Christ at his second advent.</p>

<p>And this is in accord with what our Saviour said when he foretold the</p>

<p>transfiguration.</p>

<p>“WHEN Christ, who is our life, shall appear,” there will be two classes</p>

<p>of the righteous who will “appear with him in glory”-those who have</p>

<p>fallen asleep, and those who are alive and remain unto the coming of the</p>

<p>Lord. The dead shall be raised, and the living shall be changed, and so</p>

<p>they will together be glorified. So it was when Christ was transfigured.</p>

<p>Elijah was there as the representative of those who shall be translated</p>

<p>without seeing death, and Moses, as the representative of those who fall</p>

<p>asleep. in Jesus, and whom God will bring with him from the dead. That</p>

<p>Moses had been raised from the dead when he appeared with Elijah upon</p>

<p>the mount, is proved (1) by the fact that if he had not been raised from</p>

<p>the dead he could not have been there, for “ the dead know not</p>

<p>anything.” Eccl. 9:5. See also Eccl. 9:6, 10; Ps. 6:5; 115:17; 146:3, 4;</p>

<p>Isa. 38:10, 11, 18, 19, etc. (2) Jude says that Michael (Christ)</p>

<p>contended with the devil about the body of Moses. Jude 9. The devil has</p>

<p>the power of death (Heb. 2:14) and shuts up in his prison house (the</p>

<p>grave) all that he can, claiming that they are his lawful prey (see Isa.</p>

<p>14:12-17); and although Christ has brought away the keys of the grave,</p>

<p>Satan does not willingly allow any to pass from his power. There could</p>

<p>not possibly be anything that would cause a dispute between Christ and</p>

<p>Satan about the body of Moses, except the matter of his resurrection.</p>

<p>(3) If Moses had not been raised from the dead, the transfiguration</p>

<p>would not be what both Christ and Peter declared it to be a</p>

<p>representation of the second coming of Christ.</p>

<p>BUT notwithstanding the fact that Peter had actually been an eye-witness</p>

<p>of “the power and coming” of Christ, and could testify from personal</p>

<p>knowledge, he says, “We have also a more sure word of prophecy, unto</p>

<p>which ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that shineth in a</p>

<p>dark place.” The Revised Version renders this verse as follows:” We have</p>

<p>the word of prophecy made moresure;” but we cannot accept this</p>

<p>rendering. Alford says that this rendering is on the ground,”That the</p>

<p>comparative alludes to what has gone before as its reason, as if it had</p>

<p>been said Wherefore, or Now, or Henceforth we have, etc.; i. e., ‘ on</p>

<p>account of this voice from Heaven which we have heard, we have firmer</p>

<p>hold of, or esteem \[possess\] more sure the prophetic word, as now</p>

<p>having in our own ears begun its fulfillment.’ The great objection to</p>

<p>such a view is the omission of any such connecting particles as those</p>

<p>above supplied. It is true the apostle may have omitted them \[as he</p>

<p>certainly did, and, presumably, on purpose\] ; but even supposing that;</p>

<p>it is further against the view, that if such be the force of the</p>

<p>comparison, the thought is not at all followed up in the ensuing</p>

<p>verses.”— *New Testament for English Readers*.</p>

<p>It may be further said that nothing can make the word of prophecy surer</p>

<p>than it was when it first came from the lips of the holy men whom God</p>

<p>inspired. The meaning is evidently exactly given in the common version,</p>

<p>that the sure word of prophecy is surer than any panoramic view can be.</p>

<p>Our eyes may deceive us, but the word of God “liveth and abideth</p>

<p>forever.”</p>

<p>PROPHECY is light proceeding directly from God, who is himself light.</p>

<p>With him there is “ no darkness at all.” r John r:5. In Heaven, where</p>

<p>the will of God is done perfectly, all is light. In the New Jerusalem,</p>

<p>the inhabitants “need no candle, neither light of the sun; for the Lord</p>

<p>God giveth them light.” Rev. 22:5. And when the will of God shall be</p>

<p>done on earth as it is in Heaven, the whole earth will be lightened by</p>

<p>the glory of God. “ The nations of them which are saved shall walk in</p>

<p>the light “ that comes from the city of God. Rev. 21:23, 24. But sin has</p>

<p>separated man from God, so that darkness now covers the earth. The</p>

<p>prophecy comes as a beacon-light to guide men to the source of light. As</p>

<p>with the rays from a distant light-house, the prophetic light may at</p>

<p>first be comparatively faint; but the nearer we approach to the source</p>

<p>of light, the brighter the light will become; and so of those who take</p>

<p>heed to it, it may truly be said that their path is “as the shining</p>

<p>light, that shineth more and more unto the perfect day.” Prov. 4:18.</p>

<p>” No prophecy of the Scripture is of any private interpretation.” This</p>

<p>means that Scripture is its own interpreter. For every prophecy</p>

<p>contained in the Bible, the key is found there also, and therefore every</p>

<p>prophecy is of public interpretation—the interpretation is just as</p>

<p>free to one person as it is to another. Whenever a man puts forth any</p>

<p>view as an explanation of a given prophecy, the humblest person has a</p>

<p>right to challenge his exposition, no matter how learned he may be. If</p>

<p>he cannot produce positive Scripture authority for his interpretation,</p>

<p>it must be rejected, or at least held in suspense until some wiser</p>

<p>person can find a Bible reason for the theory. The Peshito Syriac</p>

<p>version renders the verse thus:” No prophecy is an exposition of its own</p>

<p>text.” The idea is the same as that expressed above. No man can read a</p>

<p>prophecy and tell by his own unaided power, from the reading of it, what</p>

<p>it means. He must look for an exposition to some other passage, possibly</p>

<p>in the same chapter (as in Daniel 7), but still separate from the</p>

<p>prophecy itself. Spiritual things must be compared with spiritual.</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 7 – Warnings and Safety Measures.</p>

<p>APRIL 17, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 2:1-11</p>

<p>Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Read the lesson scripture.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. False teachers; their work and end, questions 1-5.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. Examples to the ungodly, questions 6-9.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. Justice of God, questions 10-12.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5.Christian purity, questions 13-15.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Remedies for presumption, questions 16-18.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. Against whom does Peter give warning? 2 Peter 2: 1, first part. Jude</p>

<p>3</p>

<p>2. What is the method of such teachers? What is the character of their</p>

<p>teaching? How does it react upon themselves? Verse 1, last part. Note 1.</p>

<p>3. What influence do their teachings have? What is the result of their</p>

<p>course? Verse 2.</p>

<p>4. What motive actuates these false teachers? What method do they</p>

<p>employ? Verse 3, first pare. Note 2.</p>

<p>5. What end awaits such teachers? Verse 3, last part.</p>

<p>6. What is the earliest example of God's dealing with persistent</p>

<p>rebellious teachers? Verse 4. Jude 6</p>

<p>7. How did God deal with unrepentant sinners in the time of Noah? Verse</p>

<p>5.</p>

<p>8. What example of the final destruction of the ungodly did God give in</p>

<p>the days of Lot? Does God destroy a sinner? Verse 6. Jude 7</p>

<p>9. What extraordinary measures did the Lord take to deliver those who</p>

<p>remained loyal to Him amid great wickedness? Verses 5-7. See Genesis,</p>

<p>chapters 6 and 19. Note 3.</p>

<p>10. What general declaration is made about the Lord's dealing with</p>

<p>men? 2 Peter 2: 9. Recall in this connection some of Peter's own</p>

<p>deliverances. See Acts 5: 17-25; 12: 1-17.</p>

<p>11. What two classes of sin are especially offensive to God? 2 Peter 2:</p>

<p>10, first part. Jude 18</p>

<p>12. After faith has wrought reconciliation of the sinner to God, what</p>

<p>is the first Christian grace to be cultivated? 2 Peter 1: 5. Read note</p>

<p>4.</p>

<p>13. What watchword does Paul give to Timothy as an example for all</p>

<p>young men and women? 1 Tim. 5: 22, last part.</p>

<p>14. What is one effective way of cultivating purity? Phil. 4: 8. Note</p>

<p>5.</p>

<p>15. What standard of purity is set before the believer? 1 John 3: 3.</p>

<p>16. What traits are prominent in despisers of government? 2 Peter 2:</p>

<p>10, last part. Jude 8</p>

<p>17. What shows that such persons boldly venture upon ground where</p>

<p>angels fear to tread? Verse 11. Jude 9</p>

<p>18. What will save the believer from getting into such a state? James</p>

<p>4: 6, 7; Eph. 5: 21; 1 Peter 2: 13-17. Note 6.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. As the defection among the angels in heaven, headed by Lucifer, was</p>

<p>at first carried on by secret insinuations and covert motives, so these</p>

<p>false teachers do their work "privily." The true follower of Jesus</p>

<p>should ever be on his guard against sly suggestions, "confidential"</p>

<p>tales, and skeptical intimations; for what looks innocent at first,</p>

<p>often leads to serious consequences, even to shipwreck of faith.</p>

<p>2. Two things are characteristic to false teachers: they speak evil of</p>

<p>the way of truth in which they once walked, and they do their evil work</p>

<p>among the believers, beguiling unstable souls, and making merchandise of</p>

<p>them to their own ends. "From such turn away."</p>

<p>3. The Lord saved Noah because he was "a just man," "perfect in his</p>

<p>generation," and because he "walked with God." But Lot, for the sake</p>

<p>of sordid gain, pitched his tent toward the cities of the plain, and</p>

<p>presently entered Sodom, dwelling among men who were "wicked and</p>

<p>sinners before the Lord exceedingly." Some of his daughters married</p>

<p>Sodomites and perished with them. Yet the Lord, at the earnest</p>

<p>entreaties of Abraham, five times repeated, saved Lot by the extreme</p>

<p>measure of sending two angels to his house, who finally had to lay hands</p>

<p>on him and draw him out of destruction.</p>

<p>4. It should be noted here that after the sinner has been reconciled to</p>

<p>God and has made every possible adjustment with his neighbor, his</p>

<p>Christian life has only begun. The seed of faith has ee n merely</p>

<p>planted; he must now cultivate the plant diligently. He has merely</p>

<p>cleared the obstructions to advancement in the strait and narrow way. He</p>

<p>has only laid the foundation of the spiritual temple for God's</p>

<p>indwell4.ing; he must now work at his own profession and build with</p>

<p>"all diligence.</p>

<p>5. For the one who is afflicted with impure, unwholesome thoughts, this</p>

<p>is a gospel remedy — keep the mind dwellingupon such wholesome,</p>

<p>uplifting things as are enumerated in this verse. As a man "thinketh in</p>

<p>his heart, so is he."</p>

<p>6. Here are three steps, given in logical order, which if taken will</p>

<p>keep a man from becoming a despiser of government or of good</p>

<p>organization of any kind: 1. Submit to God. 2. Submit to one another in</p>

<p>the fear of God. 3. Submit to every ordinance of man for the Lord's</p>

<p>sake.</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p>“In mercy to the world, God blotted out its wicked inhabitants in Noah’s</p>

<p>time. In mercy he destroyed the corrupt dwellers in Sodom…It is in</p>

<p>mercy to the universe that God will finally destroy the rejecters of his</p>

<p>grace.” (The Great Controversy p. 543)</p>

<p>**\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_**</p>

<p>“God's goodness and long forbearance, His patience and mercy exercised</p>

<p>to His subjects, will not hinder Him from punishing the sinner who</p>

<p>refused to be obedient to His requirements. It is not for a man--a</p>

<p>criminal against God's holy law, pardoned only through the great</p>

<p>sacrifice He made in giving His Son to die for the guilty because His</p>

<p>law was changeless--to dictate to God. After all this effort on the</p>

<p>part of God to preserve the sacred and exalted character of His law, if</p>

<p>men, through the sophistry of the devil, turn the mercy and</p>

<p>condescension of God into a curse, **they must suffer the penalty**.</p>

<p>Because Christ died they consider they have liberty to transgress God's</p>

<p>holy law that condemns the transgressor, **and would complain of its</p>

<p>strictness and its penalty as severe and unlike God. They are uttering</p>

<p>the words Satan utters to millions, to quiet their conscience in</p>

<p>rebellion against God**.” {12MR 208.1}</p>

<p>**\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_**</p>

<p># Lesson 8 - Warnings and Safety Measures (Continued)</p>

<p>APRIL 24, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 2:12-22</p>

<p>&gt; Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Read the lesson scripture.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. Faultfinders and critics, questions 1-3.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. Departing from the faith, questions 4, 5.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. In bondage to sin, questions '6-9.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. Turning back to sin, questions 10-12.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Hold fast to the end, question 13.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>&gt; 1.What practice is common to faultfinders and critics? 2 Pet 2:12,</p>

<p>&gt; first part. Note1.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 2. What is the result of such practice? Verse 12, last part. Jude 10</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 3. What reward will they receive? Verse 13, first part. Note 2.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 4. How is this class of evildoers further described? Verse 13, last</p>

<p>&gt; half, and verse 14. Note 3. Jude 11, 12</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 5. What have false teachers forsaken, and often from what motive?</p>

<p>&gt; Verses 15, 16.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 6. Under what figures are false teachers further described? Verse 17.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 7. What is the nature of their work? Verse 18. Jude 16</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 8. What vain promise do they make? Verse 19, first part.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 9. Why is their promise vain? Verse 19, last part. Note 4.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 10. What does Peter say to those who "have escaped the pollutions of</p>

<p>&gt; the world," then afterwards "have forsaken the right way" and sunk</p>

<p>&gt; again into sin? Verse 20. Note 5.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 11. What would have been better for these who have turned from such</p>

<p>&gt; great light? Verse 21.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 12. By what striking proverbs does Peter describe the condition of</p>

<p>&gt; one who has returned to a life of sin? Verse 22.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 13. What exhortation should we heed? Heb. 3: 12-14.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **Notes**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 1. "Speak evil of the things that they understand not." Here is the</p>

<p>&gt; key to a large amount of mischief-making, — people speaking against</p>

<p>&gt; a thing on first impression, or without sufficient knowledge of it to</p>

<p>&gt; base a judgment upon. If persons of critical temperament — in fact,</p>

<p>&gt; if all Christians everywhere — would adopt the principle of not</p>

<p>&gt; commenting upon a thing, especially to make slighting remarks about</p>

<p>&gt; it, until they understand it fully, with the reasons for it, how many</p>

<p>&gt; evils would be avoided!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 2. The cover of night is usually sought for evil. excesses of all</p>

<p>&gt; 'kinds. When people come to the place where they find pleasure in</p>

<p>&gt; such indulgences in the daytime, it is the boldness of a reprobate</p>

<p>&gt; condition. The reward of such is no worse than the reward of false</p>

<p>&gt; teachers...according to the severe arraignment of them in this</p>

<p>&gt; chapter.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 3. It is "unstable souls" that are drawn into the vortex of sin.</p>

<p>&gt; How important, then, to give all diligence to building solid elements</p>

<p>&gt; of stability into the character, according to the outline in chapter</p>

<p>&gt; 1!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 4. The greatest bondage the world has ever known — the bondage of</p>

<p>&gt; sin — originated in the despising of government, and the vain</p>

<p>&gt; promise of liberty, resulting in the final destruction of the</p>

<p>&gt; participants in the rebellion against God, and of all who have joined</p>

<p>&gt; it since. Beware of those who wear a cloak of liberty to conceal their</p>

<p>&gt; maliciousness. See 1 Peter 2:15, 16.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; 5. That there is added responsibility in a knowledge of the truth, is</p>

<p>&gt; no excuse for a man to avoid learning more of it. He is held as</p>

<p>&gt; responsible for his opportunities to know as for his actual knowledge.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; "It is impossible to estimate the good results of one 'hour or even</p>

<p>&gt; half .an hour each day devoted in a cheerful, social manner to the</p>

<p>&gt; word of God."— *Mrs. E. G. White, in "Testimonies on Sabbath</p>

<p>&gt; School Work."*</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_**</p>

<p># Lesson 9 – Surety of The Lord's Promises</p>

<p>MAY 01, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 3: 1-9</p>

<p>Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>1. **Rend the lesson scripture.**</p>

<p>2. **Mindful of the Word, questions 1-3.**</p>

<p>3. **Scoffers In the last days, questions 4-7.**</p>

<p>4. **Ignorance of scoffers, questions 8-11.**</p>

<p>5. **Know the Lord, questions 12-16**</p>

<p>6. **Duties of the believer, questions 17-20.**</p>

<p>7. **Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. What was Peter's purpose in writing his second epistle? 2 Peter 3:</p>

<p>1.</p>

<p>2. Of what would he have the believers mindful? Verse 2. Jude 17</p>

<p>3. How much is comprehended in the words of the holy prophets and the</p>

<p>commandments of the apostles? 2 Tim. 3: 16.</p>

<p>4. What would Peter have the believers know about the last days? 2</p>

<p>Peter 3: 3, first part. Jude 18</p>

<p>5. How are scoffers produced? Verse 3, last part. Note 1.</p>

<p>6. What would be the theme of their scoffing? Verse 4.</p>

<p>7. What argument do scoffers bring against the idea of the Lord's</p>

<p>coming? Verse 4, last part. Note 2.</p>

<p>8. What shows that the people of Sodom also thought all things would</p>

<p>continue? Luke 17: 28, 29.</p>

<p>9. How did it seem to those who scoffed at Noah's preaching? Matt. 24:</p>

<p>37-39.</p>

<p>10. Referring to the same event, of what does Peter say last day</p>

<p>scoffers are ignorant? 2 Peter 3: 5, 6.</p>

<p>11. What does the ignorance of scoffers in Lot's day, in Noah's day,</p>

<p>and in the last days, show? Note 3.</p>

<p>12. Although the heavens and the earth were sustained of old by the</p>

<p>word of God, of what destruction were they made the agencies? Verse 6.</p>

<p>Note 4.</p>

<p>13. What is said of the coming destruction. of the ungodly? Verse 7.</p>

<p>Note 5.</p>

<p>14. Of what are even believers in danger of being ignorant? Verse 8.</p>

<p>15. If the coming of the Lord seems to be delayed, with what must men</p>

<p>not charge Him? Verse 9, first part.</p>

<p>16. What accounts for this seeming delay? Verse 9, last part.</p>

<p>17. Of what are we assured? Heb. 10: 37.</p>

<p>18. What is our duty meanwhile? Matt. 24: 42.</p>

<p>19. What separation will be made between believers and unbelievers?</p>

<p>Verses 40, 41. 20. What fact should be an incentive to earnestness in</p>

<p>preparation to meet the Lord? Verse 44.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. "Walking after their own lusts" is the one cause above all others,</p>

<p>perhaps, that produces scoffers. These find satisfaction in turning upon</p>

<p>believers and scoffing at their "narrow," "deluded" faith and</p>

<p>practice. A pricking conscience seeks to obtain soothing by mocking at</p>

<p>the conscientious.</p>

<p>2. The strongest argument of last-day scoffers — in their minds —</p>

<p>is that "all things continue as they were from the beginning of the</p>

<p>creation." Thus it seems to the casual observer, as he looks out on a</p>

<p>perfect day, at the clear blue sky, the beautiful trees and flowers, the</p>

<p>merry birds and children. Thus, it seems also as he looks further upon</p>

<p>the wonderful progress in the arts and sciences and the spread of</p>

<p>knowledge. Yet these fail to look upon the signs the Saviour said should</p>

<p>appear in the heavens, the sea, and the things of nature and experience</p>

<p>about us. It is only the light of the Word, as Peter goes, on to show,</p>

<p>that will enable us to interpret correctly the external, material signs</p>

<p>given us, in addition to prophetic periods, as evidence of Christ's</p>

<p>soon coming.</p>

<p>3. The ignorance of scoffers at all times shows that they do not</p>

<p>receive nor study the word of God. They therefore do not know the power</p>

<p>of that Word, nor the part it acts in world events. The antediluvians</p>

<p>saw no evidence of the Flood in earth or sky. They evidently did not</p>

<p>remember how the heavens and the earth had been created (Ps. 33: 6);</p>

<p>that in their own day, the heavens and the earth "were" by the word of</p>

<p>God; and that at this same word, the course of nature could be changed</p>

<p>in a day. "The bright rays of-the morning seemed to speak only</p>

<p>prosperity and peace to the cities of the plain. The stir of active life</p>

<p>began in the streets; men were going their various ways, intent on the</p>

<p>business or the pleasures of the day. The sons-in-law of Lot were making</p>

<p>merry at the fears and warnings of the weakminded old man. Suddenly and</p>

<p>unexpectedly as would be a thunder peal from an unclouded sky, the</p>

<p>tempest broke. The Lord rained brimstone and fire out of heaven upon the</p>

<p>cities and the fruitful plain; its palaces and temples, costly</p>

<p>dwellings, gardens and vineyards, and the gay, pleasure seeking throngs</p>

<p>that only the night before had insulted the messengers of heaven, —</p>

<p>all were consumed. The smoke df the conflagration went up like the smoke</p>

<p>of a great furnace. And the fair vale of Siddim became a desolation, a</p>

<p>place never to be built up or inhabited, — a witness to all</p>

<p>generations of the certainty of God's judgments upon transgression."</p>

<p>—"Patriarchs and Prophets," p. 162.</p>

<p>4. The word "whereby" is a rendering of two words in the Greek —</p>

<p>through which, the "which" being plural in form, and therefore not</p>

<p>referring back directly to the word of God, but to the heavens and the</p>

<p>earth. In Gen. 7: 11, we read that "the same day were all-the fountains</p>

<p>of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened,"</p>

<p>the heavens and the earth uniting in producing the Flood. The</p>

<p>consideration that the things of nature which seem to "continue as from</p>

<p>the beginning of the creation," may be turned any hour, by the word of</p>

<p>God, into a means of destruction, gives much weight to Peter's teaching</p>

<p>in this chapter in reference to the coming of Christ and the final</p>

<p>destruction of the world.</p>

<p>5. "By the same word are kept in store, reserved unto fire against the</p>

<p>day of Judgment." The Revised Version, margin, reads thus: "By the</p>

<p>same word have been stored with fire, being reserved against the day of</p>

<p>Judgment." This reading makes clearer the meaning of the whole passage,</p>

<p>— that as the water stored in the heavens and the earth was turned</p>

<p>into an element of destruction at the time of the Flood, so in the day</p>

<p>of Judgment the fire stored in the heavens and the earth will be used in</p>

<p>the destruction of ungodly men.</p>

<p>**\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>**</p>

<p># Lesson 10 -The Coming of the Lord</p>

<p>MAY 8, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 3:10-18</p>

<p>Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Read the lesson scripture.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. Manner of His coming, questions 1-3.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. The Christian's attitude, questions 4-6.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. Make peace with God, questions 7-10.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. Beware and grow, questions 11-15.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Means of growth; result, questions 16-19.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1.How will the day of the Lord come? 2 Peter 3: 10.</p>

<p>2. What is the meaning of the comparison "as a thief in the night"? 1</p>

<p>Thess. 5: 2, 3. Note 1.</p>

<p>3. Upon whom will the day of the Lord not come thus? Verse 4.</p>

<p>4. What phenomena in the heavens and the earth will accompany that</p>

<p>event? 2 Peter 3: 10. Note 2.</p>

<p>5. In view of this dissolution, what question is asked the believer?</p>

<p>Verse 11. Note 3.</p>

<p>6. What should be the Christian's attitude toward the coming of the</p>

<p>Lord? Verse 12. Note 4.</p>

<p>7. For what renewal of material things may we look? What will dwell</p>

<p>there? Verse 13.</p>

<p>8. What bearing should such a prospect have on the spiritual life?</p>

<p>Verse 14.</p>

<p>9. How should we reckon the long-suffering of the Lord, even if He</p>

<p>delays His coming? Verse 15, first part.</p>

<p>10. How did Paul write his instruction to us? Verse 15, last part.</p>

<p>11. Of what things did Paul write? What did Peter say of Paul's</p>

<p>writings? How were they treated by some? Verse 16.</p>

<p>12. What classes of people wrest the Scriptures? Verse 16.</p>

<p>13. What, then, is a remedy for misusing Scripture? 2 Tim. 2: 15.</p>

<p>Answer: Increase of our knowledge of it.</p>

<p>14. To what dangers are conscientious believers exposed? 2 Peter 3: 17.</p>

<p>15. How may the believer develop stability? Verse 18, first part.</p>

<p>16. By what means can we grow in grace? 2 Peter 1: 1, 2. Note 5.</p>

<p>17. By what means can we grow in 'knowledge? Verses 5-8.</p>

<p>18. What is the assured result of multiplying grace and knowledge</p>

<p>according to the Lord's plan given us through Peter? Verse 11.</p>

<p>19. In what response may we join with Peter? 2 Peter 3: 18, last part.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. This passage of Scripture makes it clear that the point of</p>

<p>comparison is the coming suddenly or unexpectedly.</p>

<p>2. "Burned up." In the comment by Westcott and Hort on the passage,</p>

<p>other readings are given: "shall not be found," "shall disappear."</p>

<p>The whole passage is evidently intended to describe the natural results</p>

<p>of intense heat.</p>

<p>3. The effect should not be that of stimulating to greater spiritual</p>

<p>earnestness merely because of a "fearful looking for of indignation,"</p>

<p>but knowledge of such an end to material things ought to lead us not to</p>

<p>put our trust in them but to "desire a better country," a "kingdom</p>

<p>which shall never be destroyed."</p>

<p>4. The word "hasting" has the force of either hastening or desiring</p>

<p>earnestly. If we take the latter meaning, and apply it as we are</p>

<p>exhorted, it will surely lead to our helping hasten that great event.</p>

<p>5. Grace comes by faith. It is exercised toward us by applying the</p>

<p>righteousness of Christ to cover our sin. It is multiplied through the</p>

<p>increase of experimental knowledge of God.</p>

<p># Lesson 11 – Carefulness in The Christian Walk as The End Draws Near</p>

<p>May 15, 2021</p>

<p>&gt; Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **1. The blessed hope, questions 1-3.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. A warning, questions 4, 5.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. Our need, questions 6, 7.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. How should we regard time? questions S, 9.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. Our daily need, questions 10, 11.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. A special privilege; exhortations, questions 12-14.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. In view of the fact that all earthly things are soon to be</p>

<p>dissolved, what searching question are we to ask ourselves? 2 Peter 3:</p>

<p>11.</p>

<p>2. What influence will the genuine possession of the "blessed hope"</p>

<p>have upon the life? 1 John 3: 2, 3. Note 1.</p>

<p>3. Upon what is the heart to be set? Col. 3: 2-4.</p>

<p>4. What caution is given us who know these truths of the near coming of</p>

<p>the Lord? 2 Peter 3: 17.</p>

<p>5. What is said of the peril of self-confidence? 1 Cor. 10: 12.</p>

<p>6. How only may we retain possession of the truths that we know? Heb.</p>

<p>2: 1. Note 2.</p>

<p>7. Therefore, of what do those who know the truth. stand continually in</p>

<p>need? 2 Peter 1: 12, 13.</p>

<p>8. In view of the times in which we live, what exhortation is</p>

<p>appropriate? Rom. 13: 11, 12.</p>

<p>9. How should we regard time itself? Answer: As a gift from God to be</p>

<p>used to His glory. Ps. 90: 12; Eph. 5: 15, 16.</p>

<p>10. By what alone can the daily need of the soul be supplied? Matt. 4:</p>

<p>4; John 5: 39. Note 3.</p>

<p>11. Along with the feeding upon God's word, what other means of</p>

<p>spiritual strength is given? Eph. 6: 18.</p>

<p>12. What is said of the privilege of church fellowship and attendance</p>

<p>at the place of worship in the last days? Heb. 10: 23-25.</p>

<p>13. What exhortations are given regarding the influence of example on</p>

<p>those within and without the church? Heb. 12: 13; Col. 4: 5, 6. Note 4.</p>

<p>14. In what spirit are believers to await the day of redemption? Eph.</p>

<p>4: 30-32.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. The real, living hope of soon meeting Jesus transforms and shapes</p>

<p>the whole life. By faith we see Jesus hastening forward His closing work</p>

<p>in order that He may come again. He is preparing a place for us in the</p>

<p>heavenly city. John 14: 1-3. He is making intercession for us before the</p>

<p>Father's throne, that we may be prepared for the place. Heb. 7: 25. And</p>

<p>our attitude is one of watching for His coming —"looking for that</p>

<p>blessed hope." Titus 2: 13. Now we must do the work He has left us to</p>

<p>do, and be ready to meet Him.</p>

<p>2. Notice the marginal reading of the text, "run out as leaking</p>

<p>vessels." Unless the truths that we know, are kept living and bright in</p>

<p>our hearts by daily personal experience in the Lord, the level of our</p>

<p>"love of the truth" will be found sinking lower and lower,</p>

<p>imperceptibly perhaps, as' water sinks slowly in a leaking vessel. The</p>

<p>Revised Version puts it, "lest haply we drift away from them." Ships</p>

<p>do not drift into port, but are easily carried by tide and current or</p>

<p>storm on to the rocks to disaster. 3. We can no more expect to be</p>

<p>spiritually strong without feeding the soul upon the word of God, than</p>

<p>physically strong without eating our daily food. Take some Scripture</p>

<p>portion into every day's work, and let it speak to the heart again and</p>

<p>again amidst the hurry of business. It will keep the thought of God</p>

<p>near.</p>

<p>4. Every believer is marking out a path for someone else. A Swiss</p>

<p>mountaineer starting out from home along a familiar way by the edge of a</p>

<p>precipice, with little thought of where he was stepping, was startled to</p>

<p>hear a child's voice crying, "Be careful where you step, papa, for I</p>

<p>am following you." All are making footprints for someone to follow. Let</p>

<p>us carry a burden for the straying ones who may have been turned out of</p>

<p>the way by some one's Misstep. Jesus has marked the path. He is the one</p>

<p>to follow, having left "us an example, that ye should follow His</p>

<p>steps." 1 Peter 2: 21.</p>

<p>**\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>**</p>

<p># Lesson 12 – Can We Know the Time?</p>

<p>MAY 22, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 3: 10</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. Review questions: —</p>

<p>(a) Explain how Christ can come as a thief in the night and his people</p>

<p>be looking for him when he comes.</p>

<p>(b) Give four texts that prove that Christ's coming is a literal</p>

<p>coming.</p>

<p>(c) What difference will there be in the reception of-Jesus by the</p>

<p>wicked and righteous?</p>

<p>2. To whom is Christ to appear with salvation? Heb. 9:28.</p>

<p>3. What are those called who look for him? Thess. 5: 4, 5.</p>

<p>4. What is their light? Ps. 119 :105; John 8: I2.</p>

<p>5. What particular portions of the Scripture give light on the coming</p>

<p>of the Lord? 2 Peter 3: 9.</p>

<p>6. What is prophecy? See note 1.</p>

<p>7. How was prophecy written? 2 Peter 21.</p>

<p>8. What is said of the interpretation of prophecy? 2 Peter 3: 20. See</p>

<p>note 2.</p>

<p>9. If the prophet did not speak according to his own mind, who is</p>

<p>responsible for what he says? I Peter 1:10,11.</p>

<p>10. Then who instructed all the prophets what to write? See note 3.</p>

<p>11. Does Jesus make known the definite time of his second advent? Matt.</p>

<p>24:36.</p>

<p>12. How near does he come to giving us a definite time? Verse 34. See</p>

<p>note 4.</p>

<p>13. What expression does the Saviour use which shows that the term "</p>

<p>generation" means but a short period in this connection? Matt. 24:33.</p>

<p>14. What does Jesus expect his people to be doing when he is at the</p>

<p>door? Verse 42. 15. What will the unbelievers be doing in this</p>

<p>generation? 2 Peter 3:3.</p>

<p>16. What do they say? Verse 4.</p>

<p>17. What is said of their ignorance? Verse 5.</p>

<p>18. How could they have known differently? Verse 5. By the word of God.</p>

<p>19. What should those who know of the time be doing? Rom. 13: 11-14.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. PROPHECY is history written before it is made. God, who knows the</p>

<p>end from the beginning, speaks through his prophets to the world, that</p>

<p>they may know what is coming in the future, and be prepared to meet it.</p>

<p>The Saviour often spoke of himself as fulfilling the words of the</p>

<p>prophets concerning his work. Had the people given heed to the prophetic</p>

<p>Scripture, they would not have rejected him. So in the lase days they</p>

<p>that study the word of prophecy and believe it will be in the light,</p>

<p>while those who reject this word will be lost.</p>

<p>2. "THAT no prophecy of the Scripture, whether that referred to above,</p>

<p>or any other, is of any private interpretation, proceeds from the</p>

<p>prophet's own knowledge or invention, or was the offspring of</p>

<p>calculation or conjecture. The word 'epilusis' signifies, also,</p>

<p>impetus, impulse,…and probably this is the best sense here—not by</p>

<p>mere private impulse of his own mind."— Clarke.</p>

<p>3. IN 1 Peter 1:11 we learn that it was the Spirit of Christ that was</p>

<p>in the prophets that led them to speak the words they spake. In the</p>

<p>opening words of the book of Revelation, we are informed that it is a</p>

<p>"revelation of Jesus Christ," which he sent through his angel to John.</p>

<p>This angel tells John (Rev. 22:9) that he was the fellow-servant of John</p>

<p>and the other prophets before him. Then every prophet was instructed by</p>

<p>Christ's angel, and Jesus himself was the authority for all that was</p>

<p>spoken.</p>

<p>4. "BY some of the ancients a generation was fixed at a hundred years,</p>

<p>by others at a hundred and ten years, by others at thirty-three,</p>

<p>thirty-five, and even at twenty years. So that there was nothing uniform</p>

<p>and settled in this matter."—Cruden. " Genea, birth, race, descent,</p>

<p>offspring; it denotes an age, or generation from the point of view of</p>

<p>race."—Bullinger</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_</p>

<p>*“...Though no man knoweth the day nor the hour of his coming, we are</p>

<p>instructed and required to know when it is near. We are further taught</p>

<p>that to disregard his warning, and refuse or neglect to know when his</p>

<p>advent is near, will be as fatal for us, as it was for those who lived</p>

<p>in the days of Noah not to know when the flood was coming…” GC88</p>

<p>370.2*</p>

<p>***\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_***</p>

<p># Lesson 13 – Health and Temperance</p>

<p>MAY 29, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 3:11</p>

<p>&gt; Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Temperance, Questions 1-3.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. The Experience of the Christian, Questions 4-6.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. A Great Principle, Questions 7-9.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. Lessons from the Past, Questions 10-13.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. Temperance in All Things, Questions 14-17.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Read "Testimonies," Vol. 6, Pp. 369-375.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the Lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. What do we receive through the knowledge of Christ? 2 Peter 1: 3.</p>

<p>2. What quality especially touching the physical being is listed by</p>

<p>Peter among the Christian virtues? Verse 6.</p>

<p>3. Of what is temperance a fruit? Gal. 5: 22, 23. Note 1.</p>

<p>4. Through what experience does the Christian pass? Verses 24, 25.</p>

<p>5. What is required of us along with the dedication of heart and mind</p>

<p>to the service of God? Rom. 12: 1.</p>

<p>6. How does the apostle Paul urge upon Christians the proper regard for</p>

<p>the care of the body? 1 Cor. 6: 19, 20.</p>

<p>7. What did the apostle find necessary in his own experience? 1 Cor. 9:</p>

<p>27.</p>

<p>8. What principle should guide in eating and drinking? 1 Cor. 10: 31.</p>

<p>Note 2.</p>

<p>9. What is the proper aim in the matter of diet? Eccl. 10: 17. Note 3.</p>

<p>10. What contributed largely to the conditions existing before the</p>

<p>Flood? Matt. 24: 38. Note 4.</p>

<p>11. What is true of the days of Sodom? Luke 17: 28; Eze. 16: 49.</p>

<p>12. What lesson for this generation does the Saviour draw from these</p>

<p>ancient times? Luke 17: 26, 28-30.</p>

<p>13. What warning is given for this time of waiting for Christ's</p>

<p>coming? Luke 21:34, 35. Note 5.</p>

<p>14. How much is included in healthful living? 1 Cor. 9: 25.</p>

<p>15. How did Jesus on one occasion teach a lesson on temperance in work?</p>

<p>Mark 6: 31. 16. Yet how much does loyal service require of us? Mark</p>

<p>12:29, 30.</p>

<p>17. How much is included in the apostle's prayer for our</p>

<p>sanctification? 1 Thess. 5: 23.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. Temperance, or self-control, is a fruit of the Spirit. And where the</p>

<p>Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty. In Christ, we find liberation</p>

<p>from the power of every habit of self-indulgence. The spiritual nature</p>

<p>is made master over the flesh, instead of being ruled by it. There is</p>

<p>power in Christ to set men free from the drink habit, and the tobacco</p>

<p>habit, and all other habits that enslave.</p>

<p>2. These principles never change. Conditions change and human</p>

<p>requirements vary; but the principle holds always true, that every</p>

<p>Christian is under bonds to shape his life in all things to glorify God,</p>

<p>according to the light given him of, God. This emphasizes the importance</p>

<p>of becoming informed as to the principles of proper home sanitation and</p>

<p>healthful living. "*Parents should seek to awaken in their children an</p>

<p>interest in the study of physiology. Youth need to be instructed in</p>

<p>regard to their own bodies. . .. If parents themselves would obtain</p>

<p>knowledge upon this subject, and felt the importance of putting it into</p>

<p>practical use, we should see a better condition of</p>

<p>things."*—"Christian Temperance," p. 71.</p>

<p>3. The Bible rule is to eat for strength, not for mere indulgence of</p>

<p>appetite. This calls for the supply of proper food as well as the</p>

<p>elimination of unhealthful articles. "*A diet lacking in the proper</p>

<p>elements of nutrition, brings reproach upon the cause of health reform.</p>

<p>. .. Some of our people, while conscientiously abstaining from eating</p>

<p>improper foods, neglect to supply themselves with the elements necessary</p>

<p>for the sustenance of the body. Those who take an extreme view of health</p>

<p>reform are in danger of preparing tasteless dishes, making them so</p>

<p>insipid that they are not satisfying. Food should be prepared in such a</p>

<p>way that it will be appetizing as well as nourishing."*—"Testimonies</p>

<p>for the Church," vol. 9, pp. 161, 162.</p>

<p>4. "*The inhabitants of the antediluvian world were intemperate in</p>

<p>eating and drinking. They would have flesh meats, although at that time</p>

<p>God had given man no permission to eat animal food. They ate and drank</p>

<p>till the indulgence of their depraved appetites knew no bounds, and they</p>

<p>became so corrupt that God could bear with them no longer.*"</p>

<p>—"Christian Temperance," p. 43.</p>

<p>5. "SURFEIT, first, fullness and oppression occasioned by excessive</p>

<p>eating and drinking; second, to overfeed, and produce sickness or</p>

<p>uneasiness."—Webster"*When we study this question in the fear of</p>

<p>God, we shall learn that it is best, for both our physical and our</p>

<p>spiritual advancement, to observe simplicity in diet. Let us patiently</p>

<p>study this question. We need knowledge and judgment in order to move</p>

<p>wisely in this matter. Nature's laws are not to be resisted, but</p>

<p>obeyed. Those who have received instruction regarding the evils of the</p>

<p>use of flesh foods, tea and coffee, and rich and unhealthful food</p>

<p>preparations, and who are determined to make a covenant with God by</p>

<p>sacrifice, will not continue to indulge their appetite for food that</p>

<p>they know to be unhealthful. God demands that the appetites be cleansed,</p>

<p>and that self-denial be practiced in regard to those things which are</p>

<p>not good. This is a work that will have to be done before His people can</p>

<p>stand before Him a perfected people."*—"Testimonies for the</p>

<p>Church," vol. 9, pp. 153, 154.</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em></p>

<p># Lesson 14 – Sabbath Keeping.</p>

<p>JUNE 5, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 3:5</p>

<p>Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Ignorance in the last days, questions 1, 2.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. Creative power, questions 3, 4.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. A special message, questions 5-7.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. The Sabbath day, questions 8-14.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. The preparation day; a blessing promised, questions 15-17.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Read "Testimonies," vol. 6, pp. 351-359.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. Of what are unbelievers in the last days said to be willingly</p>

<p>ignorant? 2 Peter 3: 5. 2. Need anyone be ignorant of this? Heb. 11: 3.</p>

<p>3. Why is it essential to recognize the creative power in the word of</p>

<p>God? 1 Peter 1:23; John 3: 3.</p>

<p>4. What is the distinguishing feature of the true and living God? Jer.</p>

<p>10: 10-12.</p>

<p>5. What special message does God send in the last days? Rev. 14:6, 7.</p>

<p>6. By what sign may the God who "made heaven and earth" be known?</p>

<p>Eze. 20: 20. Note 1.</p>

<p>7. For what reform, then, does the last gospel message call? Isa. 56:</p>

<p>1, 2. Note 2.</p>

<p>8. When and how was the Sabbath made? Gen. 2: 2, 3.</p>

<p>9. For whom was it made? Mark 2:27.</p>

<p>10. By whom was the Sabbath made? John 1: 1-3.</p>

<p>11. How is the Sabbath to be kept? Ex. 20: 8-11.</p>

<p>12. Can an unconsecrated man keep the Sabbath holy? Matt. 7: 18.</p>

<p>13. Then what experience must accompany true Sabbath keeping? 1 John 1:</p>

<p>9; Rom. 4: 7; 5: 1. Note 3.</p>

<p>14. When does the Sabbath begin and end? Lev. 23: 32; Mark 1: 32. How</p>

<p>much of the day is holy?</p>

<p>15. What is the sixth day of the week called in Scripture? Luke 23: 54.</p>

<p>What work was to be done in the camp of Israel on the sixth day in</p>

<p>preparation for the Sabbath. Ex. 16: 23. Note 4.</p>

<p>16: How does the Lord regard carelessness or disobedience in the</p>

<p>treatment of the sacred and holy? Eze. 22: 26, 31.</p>

<p>18. What promise of blessing is made to the keepers of God's Sabbath?</p>

<p>Isa. 58: 13, 14.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. The burden of the message of Revelation 14 is a call to "*worship</p>

<p>Him that made heaven, and earth, and the sea,*" etc. This is a plain</p>

<p>reference to the terms of the fourth commandment. It is the Creator who</p>

<p>is to be recognized -in worship, whose sign or memorial is His holy</p>

<p>Sabbath. The warning of the last gospel message is against giving homage</p>

<p>to the apostasy, whose sign or mark is the rival day, Sunday.</p>

<p>2. It is at the time when the Lord says that His "salvation is near to</p>

<p>come" and His "righteousness to be revealed" that Sabbath keeping is</p>

<p>emphasized as a feature of that preparation which must be undertaken by</p>

<p>the children of men. The Lord placed a blessing on the Sabbath day; and</p>

<p>those who keep it, find the blessing. We hear this testimony from men</p>

<p>and women in. all lands. The Sabbath is a blessed gift from God to men</p>

<p>something given to us, not a day — taken from us, as appears to</p>

<p>unbelief.</p>

<p>3. Some people ask, "Do you think Sabbath keeping will save you?" Not</p>

<p>at all. In fact, we must be saved from sin by faith in Jesus in order</p>

<p>truly to keep the Sabbath. So, it is with obedience to all God's</p>

<p>commandments. We are not saved because we obey, but we obey because we</p>

<p>have found the saving grace of Christ. The call to keep the Sabbath holy</p>

<p>is in a direct way a call to holiness of life and the putting away of</p>

<p>sin.</p>

<p>4. "God requires that His holy day be as sacredly observed now as in</p>

<p>the time of Israel. The command given to the Hebrews should be regarded</p>

<p>by all Christians as an injunction from Jehovah to them. The day before</p>

<p>the Sabbath should be made a day of preparation, that everything may be</p>

<p>in readiness for its sacred hours. In no case should our own business be</p>

<p>allowed to encroach upon holy time. God has directed that the sick and</p>

<p>suffering be cared for; the labor required to make them comfortable is a</p>

<p>work of mercy, and no violation of the Sabbath; but all unnecessary work</p>

<p>should be avoided. Many carelessly put off till the beginning of the</p>

<p>Sabbath little things that might have been done on the day of</p>

<p>preparation. This should not be. Work that is neglected until the</p>

<p>beginning of the Sabbath should remain undone until it is past. This</p>

<p>course might help the memory of these thoughtless ones, and make them</p>

<p>careful to do their own work on the six working days."—"Patriarchs</p>

<p>and Prophets," p. 296.</p>

<p>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\_</p>

<p># Lesson 15 – Christian Education.</p>

<p>JUNE 12, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:3-4</p>

<p>Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt; **1. True education, questions 1-4.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. Our children, questions 5-7.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. Proper training, questions 8-10.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. Our young men and women, questions 11-14.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. A guiding principle; a high aim, questions 15-17.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Read "Education," pp. 13-19.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>*Heart Work*</p>

<p>1. What is of first importance to both young and old, in the work of</p>

<p>education? Prov. 4: 23.</p>

<p>2. What, then, may true education be said to be? Answer: Heart</p>

<p>preparation to meet the issues of life. Note 1.</p>

<p>3. In what state must the heart be to relate itself properly to the</p>

<p>issues of life? Prov. 23: 17.</p>

<p>4. What longing does the Lord express for heart work in His children?</p>

<p>Deut. 5: 29.</p>

<p>*Our Children*</p>

<p>5. What fundamental principle is given to parents on the training of</p>

<p>their children? Prov. 22: 6. Note 2.</p>

<p>6. What earnestness should parents show in this work of training? Deut.</p>

<p>6: 5-9.</p>

<p>7. Cite an example of such training. 2 Tim. 1: 5; 3: 15.</p>

<p>8. Can this kind of training be obtained in the secular schools? Note</p>

<p>3.</p>

<p>9. What provision should be made for the children of Sabbath keepers?</p>

<p>Note 4.</p>

<p>10. How should such schools be supported? Note 5.</p>

<p>*Our Young Men and Women*</p>

<p>11. What charge is given those who expect to become workers? 2 Tim. 2:</p>

<p>15. What additional admonition is given? Verse 22.</p>

<p>12. What provision is made for more advanced study? Note 6.</p>

<p>13. What is the primary object of our college work? Note 7.</p>

<p>14. Give some reason why the work of educating our children and youth</p>

<p>should be pushed vigorously. Note 8.</p>

<p>15. What must be a guiding principle in all study, in these days of</p>

<p>unbelief? Col. 2: 6-9.</p>

<p>16. What is the highest aim for a successful career? Dan. 12:3.</p>

<p>17. What words will parents, teachers, and workers for souls rejoice to</p>

<p>speak in the last day? Heb. 2: 13, last part.</p>

<p>18. What spirit and attitude are necessary in order to receive the</p>

<p>education that comes from above? Prov. 9:10; Dan. 2:20-22.</p>

<p>19. What is the ultimate objective of true education? Rom. 12:2; Col.</p>

<p>3:10. Note 9</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. In full harmony with this answer is the familiar passage in</p>

<p>"*Patriarchs and Prophets," page 595*, "The true object of education</p>

<p>is to restore the image of God in the soul."</p>

<p>2. There are seeming exceptions to this rule; but where the promised</p>

<p>result does not follow, careful examination will usually show some fault</p>

<p>in the training rather than in the principle enunciated.</p>

<p>3. In the very nature of the case, the state-supported school cannot</p>

<p>make the Bible the basis of instruction. This work can be done only by</p>

<p>the church and the parents. "Those who attend the public schools often</p>

<p>associate with others more neglected than they, those who, aside from</p>

<p>the time spent in the schoolroom, are left to obtain a street education.</p>

<p>The hearts of the young are easily impressed; and unless their</p>

<p>surroundings are of the right character, Satan will use these neglected</p>

<p>children to influence those who are more carefully trained. Thus, before</p>

<p>Sabbath-keeping parents know what evil is being done, the lessons of</p>

<p>depravity are learned, and the souls of their little ones are</p>

<p>corrupted."—"*Testimonies for the Church," vol. 6, p. 193.*</p>

<p>4. "The church has a special work to do in educating and training its</p>

<p>children that they may not, in attending school, or in any other</p>

<p>association, be influenced by those of corrupt habits."— Ibid.</p>

<p>"Wherever there are a few Sabbath keepers, the parents should unite in</p>

<p>providing a place for a day school where their children and youth can be</p>

<p>instructed. They should employ a Christian teacher, who, as a</p>

<p>consecrated missionary, shall educate the children in such a way as to</p>

<p>lead them to become missionaries. Let teachers be employed who will give</p>

<p>a thorough education in the common branches, the Bible being made the</p>

<p>foundation and the life of all study."— *Id., p. 198.*</p>

<p>5. While primarily the education of the child is the duty of the</p>

<p>parent, the training of the children of the church is a part of church</p>

<p>duty. "Feed My lambs," said Jesus to the church. "Let all share the</p>

<p>expense. Let the church see that those who ought to receive its benefits</p>

<p>are attending the school. Poor families should be assisted. We cannot</p>

<p>call ourselves true missionaries if we neglect those at our very doors,</p>

<p>who are at the most critical age, and who need our aid to secure</p>

<p>knowledge and experience that will fit them for the service of God."—</p>

<p>Id., p. 217.</p>

<p>6. "It should be the great aim in every intermediate school to do most</p>

<p>thorough work in the common branches."—"Counsels to Teachers," p.</p>

<p>210. "The word of God is to lie at the foundation of all the work done</p>

<p>in our intermediate schools. And the students are to be shown the true</p>

<p>dignity of labor." "In these schools thorough work is to be done; for</p>

<p>many students will go forth from them directly into the great harvest</p>

<p>field. They will go forth to use what they have learned, as canvassers,</p>

<p>and as helpers in various lines of evangelistic work. Many workers,</p>

<p>after laboring for a time in the field will feel the need of further</p>

<p>study, and with the experience gained in the field will be prepared to</p>

<p>value school privileges, and to make rapid advancement. Some will desire</p>

<p>an education in the higher branches of study. For these our colleges</p>

<p>have been established."— *Id., p. 203.*</p>

<p>7. "The primary object of our college was to afford young men an</p>

<p>opportunity to study for the ministry, and to prepare young persons of</p>

<p>both sexes to become workers in the various branches of the</p>

<p>cause."—"*Testimonies for the Church," vol. 5, p. 60*. "In our</p>

<p>schools the standard of education must not be lowered. It must be lifted</p>

<p>higher and still higher, far above. where it now stands; but the</p>

<p>education given must not be confined to a knowledge of textbooks</p>

<p>merely."—"*Testimonies for the Church," vol. 6, p. 126.* "While</p>

<p>attending school, the youth should have an opportunity for learning the</p>

<p>use of tools. Under the guidance of experienced workmen, carpenters who</p>

<p>are apt to teach, patient, and kind, the students themselves should</p>

<p>erect buildings on the school grounds and make needed improvements, thus</p>

<p>by practical lessons learning how to build economically. The students</p>

<p>should also be trained to manage all the different kinds of work</p>

<p>connected with printing, such as typesetting, presswork, and</p>

<p>bookbinding, together with tent making and other useful lines of work.</p>

<p>Small fruits should be planted, and vegetables and flowers cultivated,</p>

<p>and this work the lady students may be called out of doors to do. Thus,</p>

<p>while exercising brain, bone, and muscle, they will also be gaining a</p>

<p>knowledge of practical life."— *Id., p. 176*.</p>

<p>8. "It is for the honor of Christ that well educated workers should be</p>

<p>multiplied among us; they will be better able to communicate the truth</p>

<p>in a clear, intelligent way, and the truth should be presented in a way</p>

<p>that will be as free as possible from defects*."—"Christian</p>

<p>Education," p. 138.*</p>

<p>9."To restore in man the image of his Maker, to bring him back to the</p>

<p>perfection in which he was created, to promote the development of body,</p>

<p>mind, and soul, that the divine purpose in his creation might be</p>

<p>realized—this was to be the work of redemption. This is the object of</p>

<p>education, the great object of life.” Education p.15, 16</p>

<p># Lesson 16 – The Christian Home</p>

<p>JUNE 19, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:3; 3:11</p>

<p>STUDY HELPS: "The Adventist Home," pages 31-39, 105-113, 187-189,</p>

<p>292-325; "The Ministry of Healing," pages 349-394; "</p>

<p>Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Home influences, questions 1-4.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. Sacredness of marriage, questions 5-6.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. Happiness in the home, question 7.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. Christian ideals in the home, questions 8-10.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. Speaking kind words, questions 11-12.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. The Example of Joseph, questions 13-14.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. To what does Scripture liken the Christian home? Ps. 144:12. Note 1</p>

<p>2. Upon whom is the Christian home to be founded? Ps. 127:1. Note 2</p>

<p>3. What example of home training and influence is given us in</p>

<p>Abraham's experience? Gen. 18:18, 19. AH 32.1</p>

<p>4. What precious promises did God make to Jerusalem which we may claim</p>

<p>for the home where God is worshipped? Zech. 2:4, 5; Ps. 125:2. Note 3</p>

<p>5. What strong admonition does the Lord give concerning the sacredness</p>

<p>of marriage? Mal. 2:14-16. AH 85.1</p>

<p>6. What fundamental question of human relationships does the Lord</p>

<p>propound? Amos 3:3. Note 4</p>

<p>7. What basic relationship between husband and wife is essential for</p>

<p>happiness? Col. 3:18, 19. Note 5.</p>

<p>8. Upon whom rests the responsibility of teaching Christian standards</p>

<p>and ideals in the home? Deut. 6:7. AH 182</p>

<p>9. What special promise is made to children who honor and obey their</p>

<p>parents "in the Lord"? Eph. 6:1-3. Compare Deut. 5:16. AH 292, 295</p>

<p>10. What strong admonition does God give to fathers? Eph. 6:4. MH 391</p>

<p>11. What disastrous results may come from the harshness of parents?</p>

<p>Col. 3:21. Note 6.</p>

<p>12. In what spirit should correction be administered to children? Prov.</p>

<p>13:24. Compare Heb. 12:6. Note 7.</p>

<p>13. What will be the result of the right kind of training and</p>

<p>discipline in the life of the child? Prov. 22:6. Compare Heb. 12:9, 11.</p>

<p>14. How was God's promised blessing upon those who honor Him fulfilled</p>

<p>in the life of Joseph? Gen. 49:22-26. Note 8.</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. The home is the Christian's moral citadel where ideals meet their</p>

<p>severest test. It is the first line of defense against the foes from</p>

<p>without as well as from within. If the home is not governed by Christian</p>

<p>moral principles, the moral forces have suffered their greatest single</p>

<p>defeat. "The restoration and uplifting of humanity begins in the home.</p>

<p>The work of parents underlies every other. Society is composed of</p>

<p>families, and is what the heads of families make it. Out of the heart</p>

<p>are `the issues of life;' and the heart of the community, of the</p>

<p>church, and of the nation is the household. The well-being of society,</p>

<p>the success of the church, the prosperity of the nation, depend upon</p>

<p>home influences."-*The Ministry of Healing, page 349.*</p>

<p>2. Doubtless the Spirit of the Lord chose a wording of this scripture</p>

<p>which would always remind the reader that the building of a home is as</p>

<p>important as the building of a house of worship. We are told that the</p>

<p>words, "a son," "a daughter," and "a house" all come from the same</p>

<p>Hebrew word which means "to build." ' "Fathers and mothers who make</p>

<p>God first in their households, who teach their children that the fear of</p>

<p>the Lord is the beginning of wisdom, glorify God before angels and</p>

<p>before men by presenting to the world a well-ordered, well-disciplined</p>

<p>family-a family that love and obey God instead of rebelling against Him.</p>

<p>Christ is \[131 not a stranger in their homes; His name is a household</p>

<p>name, revered and glorified. Angels delight in a home where God reigns</p>

<p>supreme and the children are taught to reverence religion, the Bible,</p>

<p>and their Creator. Such families can claim the promise, `Them that</p>

<p>honor Me I will honor.' "—*The Adventist Home, pages 27, 28.*</p>

<p>3. The walls of ancient Jerusalem were no shelter for the temple</p>

<p>without the keeping power of God. Likewise, today, the artificial</p>

<p>safeguards around the family— accepted social standards, the influence</p>

<p>of the school and church, the power of the police, are no sure</p>

<p>protection against the destructive forces of our times, without the</p>

<p>abiding presence and blessing of the Lord "as a wall of fire round</p>

<p>about."</p>

<p>4. A satisfactory marriage relationship is postulated on mutual</p>

<p>understanding and agreement on basic issues. As husband and wife walk</p>

<p>together in the Lord they will find their lives continuing to blend in</p>

<p>greater unity. "To gain a proper understanding of the marriage relation</p>

<p>is the work of a lifetime. Those who marry enter a school from which</p>

<p>they are never in this life to be graduated. "However carefully and</p>

<p>wisely marriage may have been entered into, few couples are completely</p>

<p>united when the marriage ceremony is performed. The real union of the</p>

<p>two in wedlock is the work of the after years."—*The Adventist Home,</p>

<p>page 105*.</p>

<p>5. Love, companionship, and agreement are the basis for happiness in</p>

<p>marriage. "As life with its burden of perplexity and care meets the</p>

<p>newly wedded pair, the romance with which imagination so often invests</p>

<p>marriage disappears. Husband and wife learn each other's character as</p>

<p>it was impossible to learn it in their previous association. This is a</p>

<p>most critical period in their experience. The happiness and usefulness</p>

<p>of their whole future life depend upon their taking a right course now.</p>

<p>Often they discern in each other unsuspected weaknesses and defects; but</p>

<p>the hearts that love has united will discern excellencies also</p>

<p>heretofore unknown. Let all seek to discover the excellencies rather</p>

<p>than the defects. Often it is our own attitude, the atmosphere that</p>

<p>surrounds ourselves, which determines what will be revealed to us in</p>

<p>another."—*The Adventist Home, page 105.*</p>

<p>6. "But, fathers, do not discourage your children. Combine affection</p>

<p>with authority, kindness and sympathy with firm restraint. Give some of</p>

<p>your leisure hours to your children; become acquainted with them;</p>

<p>associate with them in their work and in their sports, and win their</p>

<p>confidence. Cultivate friendship with them, especially with your sons.</p>

<p>In this way you will be a strong influence for good."—*The Ministry</p>

<p>of Healing, pages 391, 392*. "Never should parents cause their children</p>

<p>pain by harshness or unreasonable exactions. Harshness drives souls into</p>

<p>Satan's net. . .. "Words that intimidate, creating fear and expelling</p>

<p>love from the soul, are to be restrained. A wise, tender, God-fearing</p>

<p>father will bring, not a slavish fear, but an element of love into the</p>

<p>home. . .. "Harsh words sour the temper and wound the hearts of</p>

<p>children, and in some cases these wounds are difficult to heal. Children</p>

<p>are sensitive to the least injustice, and some become discouraged under</p>

<p>it."—*The Adventist Home, page 308.*</p>

<p>7. "If parents work in patience and love, earnestly endeavoring to</p>

<p>help their children to reach the highest standard of purity and modesty,</p>

<p>they will succeed."— *The Adventist Home, page 208.* "To manifest</p>

<p>severity and to be exacting with children are great mistakes. Uniform</p>

<p>firmness and unimpassioned control are necessary to the discipline of</p>

<p>every family. Say what you mean calmly, move with consideration, and</p>

<p>carry out what you say without deviation. "It will pay to manifest</p>

<p>affection in your association with your children. Do not repel them by</p>

<p>lack of sympathy in their childish sports, joys, and griefs. Never let a</p>

<p>frown gather upon your brow or a harsh word escape your lips. God writes</p>

<p>all these words in His book of records."— Ibid., p. 309.</p>

<p>8."By communion with God through nature and the study of the great</p>

<p>truths handed down as a sacred trust from father to son, he \[Joseph\]</p>

<p>had gained strength of mind and firmness of principle. "In the crisis</p>

<p>of his life, when making that terrible journey from his childhood home</p>

<p>in Canaan to the bondage which awaited him in Egypt, looking for the</p>

<p>last time on the hills that hid the tents of his kindred, Joseph</p>

<p>remembered his father's God. He remembered the lessons of his</p>

<p>childhood, and his soul thrilled with the resolve to prove himself</p>

<p>true—ever to act as became a subject of the King of heaven."</p>

<p>—*Education, page 52.*</p>

<p>*\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>\<em>\</em>*</p>

<p># Lesson 17- Christian Character</p>

<p>JUNE 26, 2021</p>

<p>LESSON SCRIPTURE: 2 Peter 1:4</p>

<p>STUDY HELPS: "Christ's Object Lessons," pages 328-333; "Education,"</p>

<p>pages 225- 229; "The Seventh-day Adventist Bible Commentary," on</p>

<p>lesson texts.</p>

<p>&gt; Daily Study Outline</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **1. Fruitage of character, Questions 1-5.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **2. God’s standard of character, Questions 6-7.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **3. Builders of character, Questions 8-11.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **4. Purpose and foundation of Character Building, Questions 12-15.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **5. Illustrations, Questions 16-20.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **6. Read the Study Helps.**</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p>&gt; **7. Review the Lesson.**</p>

<p>**Questions**</p>

<p>1. According to Peter, what manner of people ought we to be? 2 Peter</p>

<p>3:11,15.</p>

<p>2. How can the Christian best glorify his heavenly Father? John 15: 8,</p>

<p>16. DA 677</p>

<p>3. What only can those who are saved from the world take with them to</p>

<p>heaven? 1 Cor. 3:13, 14; 2 Peter 1:2-4. Note 1.</p>

<p>4. What eight divine attributes does Peter name in the development of</p>

<p>Christian character? 2 Peter 1:5-8.</p>

<p>5. By what symbol does Isaiah set forth the fruitage of character in</p>

<p>the lives of God’s children? Isa. 61:3.</p>

<p>6. What is the goal of Christian character development? Matt. 5:48.</p>

<p>Note 2.</p>

<p>7. In what perfect standard is the character of God revealed? Ps. 19: 7</p>

<p>-10.</p>

<p>8. What is the only true foundation of character building? Deut. 6:24;</p>

<p>Luke 10:27. PP 34.</p>

<p>9. Where lies the responsibility for character formed in childhood?</p>

<p>Deut. 4:9; .6:20, 21.</p>

<p>10. What is the promise to God-fearing parents? Isa. 49:25, last</p>

<p>clause.</p>

<p>11. What relationship exists between God, parents, and the child? DA</p>

<p>515,516.</p>

<p>12. What is the supreme purpose to be sought in character building?</p>

<p>Prov. 6:20-22.</p>

<p>13. What is one of the first requisites of character building?</p>

<p>ANSWER—Obedience. Heb. 5:8; Eph. 6:1. Note 3</p>

<p>14. Name another cardinal virtue that must be established in childhood.</p>

<p>ANSWER—Faithfulness. Ps. 31:23; Matt. 25:21, 23; Rev. 2:10. Note 4.</p>

<p>Note 5.</p>

<p>15. Name a third virtue essential to a firm and steadfast character.</p>

<p>ANSWER—Honesty. Prov. 11:1; Rom. 12:17, last clause; Phil. 4:8, first</p>

<p>three phrases</p>

<p>16. How are those just converted to Christ described by Peter? 1 Peter</p>

<p>2:2.</p>

<p>17. What do they desire? 1 Peter 2:2, *second part*</p>

<p>18. For what purpose? 1 Peter 2: 2, *last clause*</p>

<p>19. What other symbols are employed to represent the Christian growth?</p>

<p>Hosea 14:5-7.</p>

<p>20. What agency is employed by the believers in order to give fruit in</p>

<p>due season? James 5:7; Ps. 1:1-3. COL 61.2</p>

<p>**Notes**</p>

<p>1. "It is a solemn thing to die, but a far more solemn thing to live.</p>

<p>Every thought and word and deed of our lives will meet us again. What we</p>

<p>make of ourselves in probationary time, that we must remain to all</p>

<p>eternity. Death brings dissolution to the body, but makes no change in</p>

<p>the character. The coming of Christ does not change our characters; it</p>

<p>only fixes them forever beyond all change."-*Testimonies, vol. 5, p.</p>

<p>466.*</p>

<p>2. "The ideal of Christian character is Christlikeness. As the Son of</p>

<p>man was perfect in His life, so His followers are to be perfect in their</p>

<p>life."—*The Desire of Ages, page 311*. "By His perfect obedience He</p>

<p>has made it possible for every human being to obey God's commandments.</p>

<p>When we submit ourselves to Christ, the heart is united with His heart,</p>

<p>the will is merged in His will, the mind becomes one with His mind, the</p>

<p>thoughts are brought into captivity to Him; we live His life. This is</p>

<p>what it means to be clothed with the garment of His righteousness, . . .</p>

<p>which is perfect obedience to the law of Jehovah."—*Christ's Object</p>

<p>Lessons, page 312.*</p>

<p>3. "One of the first lessons a child needs to learn is the lesson of</p>

<p>obedience. Before he is old enough to reason, he may be taught to obey.</p>

<p>By gentle, persistent effort, the habit should be established. Thus, to</p>

<p>a great degree, may be prevented those later conflicts between will and</p>

<p>authority that do so much to create alienation and bitterness toward</p>

<p>parents and teachers, and too often resistance of all authority, human</p>

<p>and divine."— *"Education," p. 287.* "Rules should be few and well</p>

<p>considered; and when once made, they should be enforced. Whatever it is</p>

<p>found impossible to change, the mind learns to recognize and adapt</p>

<p>itself to; but the possibility of indulgence induces desire, hope, and</p>

<p>uncertainty, and the results are restlessness, irritability, and</p>

<p>insubordination."— *"Education," p. 290*</p>

<p>4."Only by faithfulness in the little things can the soul be trained</p>

<p>to, act with fidelity under larger responsibilities."—"*Christ's</p>

<p>Object Lessons," p. 356*. "Christ in His life on earth taught the</p>

<p>lesson of careful attention to the little things. The great work of</p>

<p>redemption weighed continually upon His soul. As He was teaching and</p>

<p>healing, all the energies of mind and body were taxed to the utmost; yet</p>

<p>He noticed the most simple things in life and in nature. His most</p>

<p>instructive lessons were those in which by the simple things of nature</p>

<p>He illustrated the great truths of the kingdom of God. He did not</p>

<p>overlook the necessities of the humblest of His servants. His ear heard</p>

<p>every cry of need. He was awake to the touch of the afflicted woman in</p>

<p>the crowd; the very slightest touch of faith brought a response. When He</p>

<p>raised from the dead the daughter of Jairus, He reminded her parents</p>

<p>that she must have something to eat. When by His own mighty power He</p>

<p>rose from the tomb, He did not disdain to fold and put carefully in the</p>

<p>proper place the graveclothes in which He had been laid</p>

<p>away."—"*Christ's Object Lessons," pp. 357, 358.*</p>

<p>5. "It is neither the magnitude nor the seeming insignificance of a</p>

<p>business transaction that makes it fair or unfair, honest or dishonest.</p>

<p>By the least departure from rectitude we place ourselves on the enemy's</p>

<p>ground, and may go on, step by step, to any length of injustice. A large</p>

<p>proportion of the Christian world divorce religion from their</p>

<p>business."—"*Testimonies," vol. 4, p. 337*. "These truths are not</p>

<p>for the closet more than for the counting room. The goods that we handle</p>

<p>are not our own, and never can this fact safely be lost sight of. We are</p>

<p>but stewards, and on the discharge of our obligation to God and man</p>

<p>depend both the welfare of our fellow beings and our own destiny for</p>

<p>this life and for the life to come."—"*Education," p. 139.*</p>

<p>**Further thoughts.**</p>

<p>1.It should be noted here that after the sinner has been reconciled to</p>

<p>God and has made every possible adjustment with his neighbor, his</p>

<p>Christian life has only begun. The seed of faith has been merely</p>

<p>planted; he must now cultivate the plant diligently. He has merely</p>

<p>cleared the obstructions to advancement in the strait and narrow way. He</p>

<p>has only laid the foundation of the spiritual temple for God's</p>

<p>indwelling; he must now work at his own profession and build with "all</p>

<p>diligence."</p>

<p>2. Understanding the elements of Christian character:</p>

<p>*Faith*: belief to the saving of the soul. Heb. 10: 39.</p>

<p>*Virtue:* habitual purity of thought and action; and unwavering courage,</p>

<p>lacking in Peter's early experience.</p>

<p>*Knowledge:* faith and virtue without enlightenment are like steam in</p>

<p>the boiler of an engine without the intelligent hand to direct it in</p>

<p>effective service. "My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge."</p>

<p>"Fools hate knowledge."</p>

<p>*Temperance:* self-control. Besides the steam and the engineer, the</p>

<p>engine must have its "governor" to regulate its action. The</p>

<p>acquisition of knowledge must not become an uncurbed passion; its proper</p>

<p>use is what tells. Temperance is self-control in all things to the</p>

<p>extent of non-indulgence in hurtful practices, and of moderation in good</p>

<p>ones.</p>

<p>*Patience*: endurance. "Not weary in well-doing." It is not enough to</p>

<p>pursue virtue, knowledge, and temperance for a time, or spasmodically;</p>

<p>it must be a continuous perseverance in well-doing.</p>

<p>*Godliness:* literally, reverence toward God,' spiritual mindedness.</p>

<p>Unbelievers often cultivate patience, temperance, knowledge, and virtue,</p>

<p>but they do not cultivate these qualities for the honor and glory of</p>

<p>God. The believer's cultivation of these graces must have in it the</p>

<p>spiritual mind, the unselfish motive — of honor to God and blessing to</p>

<p>his neighbor.</p>

<p>*Brotherly kindness*: literally, brotherly love. Disinterested kindness</p>

<p>and loving service to a brother, friend, neighbor, or enemy, is one of</p>

<p>the highest practical tests of love to God. The keeping of the last six</p>

<p>commandments is the natural fruitage of keeping the first four.</p>

<p>*Charity*: love. The keeping of all the commandments— the result of</p>

<p>developing the previous seven graces of character.</p>

<p>The virtues enumerated here are often called "Peter's ladder," and</p>

<p>very properly. Another conception would be "Peter's rainbow"; for as</p>

<p>the seven colors of the rainbow combine to form white light, so the</p>

<p>seven traits of Christian character enumerated by the apostle blend into</p>

<p>the one supreme virtue, charity or love.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>